<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rarities of Turkey, gathered by one that was sold seven times a slave in the Turkish Empire, and now exposed to view for the benefit of his native countrey:.</title>
            <author>Georgijević, Bartolomej, d. ca. 1566.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1921A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175972</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51784492</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51784492</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174907</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02743)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174907)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2705:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rarities of Turkey, gathered by one that was sold seven times a slave in the Turkish Empire, and now exposed to view for the benefit of his native countrey:.</title>
                  <author>Georgijević, Bartolomej, d. ca. 1566.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 125, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata, p. [18]</note>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed Bartholomeus Georgieviz, p. [10]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Islam --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Islam --  Relations --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History --  Ottoman Empire, 1288-1918 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  Social conditions --  1288-1918 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RARITIES OF TURKEY, GATHERED By one that was ſold ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times a Slave in the Turkiſh Empire, AND Now expoſed to view for the benefit of his Native Countrey:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for the Author 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend and Illuſtrious, CARDINAL <hi>de</hi> MONTE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE horrible fierce Diſcordances, and inteſtine Civil Wars of Chriſtian Princes, had reduc'd me (moſt noble Cardinal) to this condition, That being deſpoyl'd and plundered of all Eſtate, bound in Chains, and haled thorow the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainous &amp; dangerous Paſſages
<pb facs="tcp:174907:3"/>of <hi>Thracia</hi> and leſſer <hi>Aſia,</hi> dragged about from place to place, like horſe unto a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, I became ſeven times ſold to the ſundry and toyleſome ſorts of ruſtick labors; where under an heavy <hi>Turkish</hi> rod, &amp; ſharper provocations, in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirſt, in cold and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, expoſed to all open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Airs, I was compell'd to attend the feeding Sheep, Goats, and all other ſorts of Cattel, and oftentimes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe their diſcipline of war. For prevention therefore of a laſting miſery, I endeavoured an eſcape; and wandering up and down, guided by the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern
<pb facs="tcp:174907:3"/>Pole, ſuſtaining Life with Acorns, wilde herbs, and their bitter roots, ſodden with a little ſalt, I ſpent my time in ſolitarineſs, amidſt even ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Beaſts; till at length, having faſtned together ſome few Timber pieces with cords and wythes, I ventured to paſs the Helleſpontick Sea; but was retaken, and brought back again unto my Maſter; where tyed both hands and feet, and proſtrated on the ground, I was moſt cruelly and ſeverely ſcourged and threſhed; and after, for the ſpace of thirteen yeers, toſſed and tumbled on the waves of
<pb facs="tcp:174907:4"/>a ſad and adverſe fortune un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Turkiſh Government. I endured and ſuffered many miſeries, calamities, afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and perſecutions for my Religions ſake.</p>
            <p>But when I had found by ſad exprience, that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer more compendious way through <hi>Thrace,</hi> could not free me from their Tyranny, and grievous Slavery, I reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſteer another courſe by obſervation of the Southern Pole, to paſs the Deſarts and perillous places of <hi>Caramania</hi> and <hi>Syria:</hi> and ſo through many and various difficulties, I at length arrived in the holy
<pb facs="tcp:174907:4"/>Land, and was received by the Brethren of Saint <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> inhabiting Mount <hi>Sion:</hi> from whence, after the refreſhment of a yeer, as a man revived from death, (by God's Almighty providence) and as ſnatched from the claws of the helliſh Dragon, &amp; freed from thoſe cruel tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I return'd home amongſt my Chriſtian Friends, a true witneſs of the Turkiſh cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; that they with due repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for their ſins and errors, might learn to avoid like cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyings and tortures; and likewiſe underſtand what high degree of hate thoſe men
<pb facs="tcp:174907:5"/>deſerve, whoſe foul ambitions ſtop and hinder the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſtian ſwords from deſtructing and aboliſhing that Satanick-Turkiſh Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which may (by God's aſſiſtance) be the only preventor of our future mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries; and which hath been long-ſince, and propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſpoken of, both by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Infidels.</p>
            <p>Therefore having finiſhed a large perambulation of the holy Land, and viſited good part there of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed rudely the Tragedy of their cruelties, together with other circumſtances of that
<pb facs="tcp:174907:5"/>Government, all which I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd from daily converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, experience, &amp; long practiſe in Courts and Camps of the Turkiſh Emperour; and what more I could ever learn from ratiocinations with wiſe and experienced men, or by read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I committed ſtil to memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and at ſeveral times &amp; ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, remitted them to writing, and made them after publick; which divers learned and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber perſons tranſlated into their ſeveral Idiomes: which when I found, and perceived they might prove neceſſary, or ſomewhat uſeful, &amp; favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably accepted by the Reader,
<pb facs="tcp:174907:6"/>I recollected them, and bound them up into this little bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, and have dedicated the whole unto your Grace, the beſt of Patrons, printed in this famous City, <hi>Rome,</hi> receptacle of all Natoins, to be difperſed to all Friends and Strangers.</p>
            <p>Do you therefore by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our Saviour Chriſt, who preferred the poor Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows mite, before the gifts of Princes, &amp; with that purchaſed the inheritance of immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, favourably &amp; in good part accept of this poor oblation, from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt devoted Servant, <hi>Bartholomeus Georgie viz,</hi> Pilgrim.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:6"/>
            <head>THE PILGRIM TO HIS Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Once had fixed my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (worthy Reader) that theſe my poor endeavours ſhould come abroad (for your utility and pleaſure) in a far comlier habit, cloathed with
<pb facs="tcp:174907:7"/>augmentation of Arguments, and more p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ed Expreſſions: but my poverty, and nakedneſs of neceſſary Implements, diverted all ſuch thoughts, and ſtop'd my undertaking ſuch a labour; wanting beſides both time and place of fit retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for ſtudious deſires.</p>
            <p>Sumptuous and ſmooth Garments, or Men well moneyed, have onely entrance into Princes Palaces, and great Mens Gates; that if n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w <hi>Homer</hi> ſhould even himſelf otherwiſe appear, a rude and ſurly Porter thruſts him out of doors. And I confeſs in conſcience, in this degenerate Age, men take more pleaſure, ſpend more thoughts and money in ſcul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, picture, hawking, hunting, and worſer things, unneceſſary, then in due obſervance of our Saviour Chriſt's exemplary divine moralities, then in the ſervice and advancement of their Laws and Country, or relieving wants of diſtreſſed poor or Pilgrims, Do y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u not ſo, (good Christian Reader;)
<pb facs="tcp:174907:7"/>but first in all humility, and reverence, obey, and worſhip your Great God, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, and Redeemer; next, be more careful to ſupply the needy and poor-Man, who is a Temple of Chriſt, an Habitation of the Holy Ghoſt: then, not onely love and ſtudy the proſperity of your Country, (which God exacts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all private intereſts) but love all good Supporters of your just Laws and liberties, and all true Patriots there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And if you ſhall receive by this my pains, the leaſt of delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, impute it not to your well-wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing PILGRIM, but the benignity and liberality of his noble PATRONS and BENEFACTORS: and where you finde Him paſs the limits of Sobriety or Modeſty, or to come ſhort and flat in Elecution, let your great prudence and humanity correct Him; and be pleaſed to conſider Him, to have ſpent the ablest and best portion of his time and Age, in rude and rustick ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitudes,
<pb facs="tcp:174907:8"/>under the Turkiſh Nation, and not in application to liberal Arts and Sciences.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farwel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:8"/>
            <head>The TRANSLATOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>HE that deſires to move compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſuch-like affections in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, muſt have ſome ſympathy and natural inclination thereto himſelf. The peruſal of this ſmall Treatiſe, brought ſadneſs to my thoughts, and tears into my eyes, even to a fellow-feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the bitter and diſaſtrous conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſtian Captives. What heart ſo flinty, as to forbear lamenting for them? The rigid old opinion of ſome Stoicks, who fancied &amp; taught not be grieved at
<pb facs="tcp:174907:9"/>any event, Not to be diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rbed with dolency at any accident befals mortality, is a doctrine no way ſuitable to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. All man muſt be reſigned, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred, unman'd, and quite put off, if affections be taken from him. The ſence and tenderneſs whereof, wrought me to this Tranſlation: and remembred thereby, to praiſe and glorifie our good and gracious God, who hath preſerved us from ſuch calamities; and likewiſe hoping to encreaſe the number of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting mindes, and charitable diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. My poverty and weak capacity, could finde no other means to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental for them. Thick and dark clouds have eclipſed the warmth and comfort of the Sun from me: but, <hi>Be you merciful, as your heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is merciful.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:9"/>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:10"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Page.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Line.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>for <hi>and paid,</hi> read <hi>are paid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>put out <hi>Troy-weight.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>28.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>for <hi>teh,</hi> read <hi>the.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Paſſengers,</hi> read <hi>Paſſages.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>79.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>do kill,</hi> read <hi>do not kill.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>102.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>for <hi>their fenars,</hi> read <hi>their defenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>117.</cell>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>for <hi>drunk,</hi> read <hi>drink.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>123.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>for <hi>Rocks,</hi> read <hi>Rocks.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174907:10"/>
            <head>Of the Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the <hi>TURKS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">CHAP. I.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Oratories.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fabricks of their Churches are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently large and ſumptuous, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the name of <hi>Meſchites:</hi> in which I never could perceive any ſort of fancies or imageries (for Idolatry is held by them the worſt of abominations)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174907:11"/>but onely theſe, or one of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions following, in the Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick Language, <hi>There is no God but one, and Mahomet his Prophet;</hi> or, <hi>One Creator and Prophets equal:</hi> or, <hi>None is ſtrong as God.</hi> Then there is ſeen a great abundance of burning Lamps, the whole Church whited, the Pavement covered with Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, and on them the Ornaments of Tapeſtries. Neer the Church, is erected a Tower of great height, to the top whereof the Prieſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cends before the time of Prayers, and with a loud voice, his ears ſtopped with his fingers, he thrice proclaims theſe words; <hi>God, True, One:</hi> which Clamour or Outcry (for they have no Bells) being heard, the Nobility, and all unbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied perſons, repair to Church, as bound to that devotion. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſaid Prieſt deſcending, prays with them; (and then they turn their faces towards <hi>Mecha:)</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:174907:11"/>And this he is tyed to do by his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, five times day and night. But whoſoever cometh to theſe Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, muſt waſh his hands, his feet, and privities, and his head thrice ſprinkled with water, and theſe words pronounced: <hi>Glory to my God.</hi> Then, their ſhooes put off, and left at the Church-door, they enter in, ſome bare-footed, others having new Shooes or Socks, and ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly touch the ground. Women come not into Churches, as being not excis'd, and for fear of diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens devotions; but meet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in ſevered places, altogether ſhut off from eyes and ears of men; and more ſeldome frequent their Churches, except in time of Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, or Eaſter, and on Fridays; which days, from <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, for diſtinction and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they almoſt reſpect as much as Jews their Sabbaths, or Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans the Lords day. They pray
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174907:12"/>from nine a clock at night till twelve; and in their praying, their bodies are ever in great motion and agitation, wherewith they marvelouſly afflict themſelves, with loud cryings and fierce ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; ſo as oftentimes, their ſtrengths and ſpirits failing, they ſink unto the ground; and if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, any of them conceive her ſelf with child, ſhe then aſſures her ſelf, that pregnancy proceeds from fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Holy Spirit; and when delivered, the Infants born are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Sons,</hi> or <hi>Souls of the Holy Ghost.</hi> This hath been related to me from their Hand-maids; for I, nor ever any man elſe, were preſent at that ſpectacle. At mens devotions I have been often preſent with my Maſter; whoſe cuſtomes are in manner following: in their prayers they ne'er take off (their Turbants) coverings of their heads, but with the tops of their fingers gently
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174907:12"/>touch them, in token of taking them off; they fall upon their knees and often kiſs the ground: they hold it for great wickedneſs, to have a Chriſtian preſent at their myſteries; for they believe their Churches (as they ſay) to be polluted by men unwaſhed; and that Chriſtians uſe not ſuch Lavatories. Every Church in <hi>Turky</hi> hath a peculiar place for Baths and waſhings, with lodgings for a Prieſt. Now here the Prieſt aſcends his Pulpit (reads a piece of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and ſometimes expounds it) and there preaches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two hours; his Sermon end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, two boyes come up to him, who pronounce their prayers ſinging with reſponſals; which Songs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, the Prieſt with the whole People in a low voice, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon their ſides, repeat theſe words, <hi>There is but one God;</hi> which for the ſpace of half an hour they do, and ſo depart. But this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174907:13"/>manner of Prayers and Ceremonies of Preaching and ſinging, are not done every day, unleſs in time of Lent, Feſtivals, ſome Sundayes; and moſt obſerve the Fridayes for religious worſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Lent.</head>
               <p>THey keep their Lent by faſting one Month and one Week e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Year; but not alwayes the ſame: for if this Year they faſt out <hi>January,</hi> the next they faſt out <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> and keep on that courſe; ſo as in twelve Years ſpace, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate to God (in lieu of tenths) one Year and twelve Weeks. Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and ſick Perſons are excuſed from preſent faſtings; but are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to ſupply it, by faſting ſo many dayes at other times. When they faſt, all that Day they taſte nothing, not ſo much as Bread or Water; then the Stars appearing,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174907:13"/>it is lawful for them to eat of all things which are not ſtrangled, or Hoggs-fleſh, which they eſteem as carrion, moſt unclean. Their Lent being paſt, they obſerve <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> for three dayes, with great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, anoynting the Nails of their Feet and Fingers with an Oyl which they call <hi>Chna,</hi> which maker thoſe Nails to ſhine like Gold; and with the ſame, they ſomtimes ſtain or colour the Hoofs and Tails of Horſes. This Tincture holds very long, &amp; can hardly be wip'd away; ſo, as until new Nails thruſt out the old, they ſtill retain that dye: but Nails of the Hand, by frequent waſhing, abate in time. Women do not onely anoynt the Nails, but their whole Hands and Feet alſo with that Oyl.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:174907:14"/>
               <head>Of their Circumciſion.</head>
               <p>THey Circumciſe not on the eighth day, as the <hi>Jews</hi> do, but when the new-born arrive at the age of ſeven or eight yeers, and be of perfect ſpeech: the myſtery whereof, is from the words of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion required before circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which are ſome of thoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences afore-mentioned in their Churches, which they repeat, and give aſſent thereto, by hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Thumbe of the right-Hand. The Youth is not for this myſtery brought unto their church, but is circumciſed in his Parents Houſe. I have been often preſent at this ſolemnity, which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in manner following: firſt, the friends are all invited to a feaſt, ſufficiently furniſhed with all ſorts of delicate fleſh, lawful for them to eat; and almoſt everywhere, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174907:14"/>amongſt the wealthier ſort, an Ox is killed, bowelled, and flawed; in the body whereof, they include a Sheep; and in that Sheep, a Hen; and in her, an Egge; all which are entirely roaſted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the ſolemnity and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of that day. Then in their Feaſt and time of Supper, the Boy that is to be circumciſed, is brought to a Phyſitian skilful in that Art, who fixing between a pair of pinchers the fore-skin of his privie Member, to prevent all fear in the Boy, he telleth him, that the next day he will circumciſe him, and ſo departs; but preſently feigning to have omitted ſomething appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this preparation, on a ſudden he cuteth off the fore-skin, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto a little ſalt and bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bace; and then he is called a <hi>Muſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> that is, one circumciſed. Yet their Names are given the day of their Nativity, not Circumciſion.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174907:15"/>After continuance of this Feaſt for three dayes, the Boy with great pompe and ſolemnity is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to the Bathes; and being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his Houſe, he is brought before the Gueſts, and by them preſented with gifts prepared for him; ſome give Silver, Silken Veſtments; ſome, Silver Cups; others, Money; and ſometimes, Horſe. Women preſent him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſome, with Shirts, Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchers, and ſuch like, according to the ſeveral pleaſures and abilities of the Gueſts. Women are not circumciſed, onely they confeſs the aforeſaid words, and ſo made <hi>Muſſelmen.</hi> And if any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an voluntarily confeſs a Faith in <hi>Mahomes,</hi> and ſuffers Circumciſion, (which often happens, by the heavy yoke and burthen of their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute) this Man is led through all the Streets and open places of the City, to the great joy and honour
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174907:15"/>of the people, with acclamations and ringing of Bells: him alſo they preſent with gifts, and after free him from all Tribute. For covetouſneſs of this profit, many <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Albanes</hi> become cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed. But if any be forced thereto, as he that ſhall ſtrike or otherwiſe diſgrace a <hi>Muſſelman,</hi> or blaſpheme <hi>Mahomet,</hi> (as it befel a certain <hi>Grecian Biſhop</hi> which I did ſee) that man is circumciſed, and hath nothing preſented to him, yet ſhall be freed from Tribute as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers circumciſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Prieſts.</head>
               <p>THeir great Muſty (as the Pope among Catholiks) cannot erre, and is the higheſt Miniſter of all Religious and Lay Perſons: an Officer of great power and truſt: his concluſions and ſentences in State and Church-affairs, are irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174907:16"/>and his perſon held in moſt eſteem and reverence next the Emperour: his habit moſt in green, being <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s colour. There is ſmall difference between their other Prieſts and Lay-men, nor much from the Governours of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies (ſuch as our <hi>Biſhops</hi> are) neither is much learning required from them: it is ſufficient, if they can read the <hi>ALCORAN</hi> and <hi>MUSSAPH;</hi> yet they that can interpret on the Text, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed moſt learned, becauſe the Traditions of <hi>Mahomet</hi> are written in the <hi>Arabick,</hi> not vulgar <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Character; and they hold it for moſt deteſtable, to have them interpreted in the vulgar Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. Theſe Prieſts and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours are elected by the People; but their rewards are ſtipends for their labours, and paid by the King. They have Wives, and Habits like Seculars: and if their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174907:16"/>ſtipends be not ſufficient to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the number of their Children, they otherwiſe ſupply themſelves by Handicrafts, and Trades, or what elſe befits a Free-man; as teaching Schooles, tranſcribing Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ne'er could ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them any Printers; but Paper is there very well made. Some make profit one way, ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as Taylors, Shooe-makers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Monks.</head>
               <p>THey have likewiſe Monks of ſeveral Orders; but chiefly of theſe three: the firſt have no propriety in any thing, they go al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt wholly naked, ſaving their privities covered with a Sheep's skin, and in cold weather they uſe the like to cover their backs; their ſides, their feet and hands, are never covered. They beg alms as well
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174907:17"/>of Chriſtians as Turks; and, <hi>For God's ſake.</hi> Theſe Monks having eaten an Herbe called <hi>Maſlach,</hi> are poſſeſt with a kinde of fury and madneſs; they cut and wound their breſts croſs and overthwart, and ſo their arms, diſſembling all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or pain; then clap on their heads, hands, and breſts, the ſpunge or muſhrooms of old Trees light burning, and not remove them till they are reduced to aſhes. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Order I have ſeen, who go with their privy part bor'd tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and a Ring included of the weight of three pound <hi>Troy</hi>-weight; and this to preſerve chaſtity. The third Order is rarely ſeen abroad; but remain both day and night in Churches, where within ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Angles they have ſmall Cabins, no ſhooes, veſtments; or coverings of the head, wearing nothing but one ſhirt; their exerciſe is faſts and prayers, that God would reveal
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174907:17"/>things future to them. With this ſort of Monks, the King of Turks uſually conſults, when he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends a motion or expedition to War.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Their reverence to <hi>Mahomet's</hi> Traditions.</head>
               <p>THey give ſo much reſpect to <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Traditions and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, that, not onely they never blaſpheme GOD or his Prophet; (which amongſt us ſometime hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens) but if they finde the leaſt leaf or ſcrowl thereof, lying on the ground, they take it up and often kiſs it, and place it on ſome ſhelves or chinks of walls; affirming it a ſin, to ſuffer that wherein the Name of God, and Laws of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> are written, to be trodden under foot. And no man dares to ſell the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and other writings of their Law, to any <hi>Christian,</hi> or any
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174907:18"/>other differing in Religion or Faith with them, leſt they ſhould be trodden on, or touched with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean hands: and whoſoever ſhould ſo do, is ſeverely puniſhed. And in this regard they may be ſtiled farre more reverent then <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Schools.</head>
               <p>THey have places for Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Teachers both of Men and Women: in ſeveral Towns, Men, the Boyes; and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Girls: ſome teach Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, Phyſick; and ſome, the Art of Poetry; which when they do, they ſpeak out with loud voyce; and moving their hands unto their ſides, they pronounce their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. They underſtand no artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Muſick; but frame verſes to certain rules, which conſiſt of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſillables. The hotneſs of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174907:18"/>Clymate, &amp; often ſickneſſes, makes moſt inclined to Phyſick, wherein they have ſome ſmall knowledge. They learn Aſtronomy, to be thought able to tell fortunes. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is ſupplied by a number of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Prieſts; and perhaps neglected (as all learning is) to maintain the peoples ignorance, and keep them off from ſearch into the groſs ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities of their conſtrained Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Marriages.</head>
               <p>THey marry without Vowes or Oathes, take Wives without portions, and for the moſt part buy them; contrary to the Roman cuſtome, where the Son in law was bought with Money to take a Daughter. This married Woman carries nothing with her for uſe or ornament, which ſhe is not forced to redeem or purchaſe from her
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174907:19"/>Parents. Evil manners or ſterility, are cauſes of Divorces; for which there is a peculiar Judge. They permit their bond-men or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed ſervants to marry; but the iſſue of them are all born ſlaves. The <hi>Alcoran</hi> perſwadeth marriage, as pleaſing God and Man; and it allows plurality of Wives and Concubines, as many as Man pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. The Turk amongſt his (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he hath above five hundred in his Seraglio's) nameth her for his Wife or Sultana, by whom he hath his firſt-begotten Son. All their Wives are uſed with equality of reſpect, in diet, cloaths, returns, and what concerns them; and are moſt obedient to their Husbands. They nurſe their own Children, and bear them on their Shoulders, not in their Arms: no men, but Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuchs, are ſuffered to be with them, not their own Sons, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove twelve years of age: they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174907:19"/>go abroad, but accompanied with onely Women.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Strangers.</head>
               <p>PIlgrims of ſeveral Nations tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel to viſit holy places, which the Turk poſſeſſeth; as <hi>Mecha</hi> and <hi>Medinum,</hi> (as Chriſtians, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) where they ſay <hi>Mahomet</hi> was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but this is done as well for gain and profit, as for devotion or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions ſake. And there having ſeen a gilded Shoo hanging from the roof of the Church, &amp; bought ſuch fine linen and cloath as they pleaſe, they return home with great advantage; ſome carrying about the Streets, water, from thence, in glaſſes, for devotions ſake, and freely give it to any that are thirſty; others, do the like for profit. And if any one of them happen to die in this Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, by what occaſion ſoever, although he ne'er arrive neer <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:174907:20"/>yet he hath the eſtimation, and ſhall be placed in the rank of Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Miracles done by <hi>Mahomet</hi> at <hi>Mecha,</hi> which, they ſay, he ſtill doth in theſe times.</head>
               <p>I Know not whether I ſhould call them Miracles, or rather Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous toyes, written in their book called <hi>Mehemedine,</hi> wherein they are perſwaded, that when <hi>Mecha</hi> was a building, GOD, by the prayers of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> commanded divers moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to bring their ſtone to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of that Church, every Hill his tenth: and when divers Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains had brought their portions, and <hi>Mecha</hi> built and perfectly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, a certain Hill called <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> and ſome other more remote, coming thither with their tenths ſomewhat too late, and finding <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha</hi> built, and no uſe of their ſtones,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174907:20"/>they began moſt bitterly to weep; which when <hi>Mahomet</hi> perceived Hills ſo diſtreſſed, and underſtood the cauſe, he ſaid unto them, <hi>Be of good cheer, weep not, but ſtore your tenths up in a place which I ſhall ſhew you; and whoſoever ſhall not pray upon your ſtones, his pilgrimage ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and unaccepted.</hi> And after ſo doing, <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſtruck the ſtones with his foot, and there iſſued out Water, not uſeful to drink; and impoſed a name, and called it, <hi>A water of purification,</hi> whereof every Pilgrim carrieth at his return, ſome portions thereof in veſſels; and whenever any die, the veſtures wherewith the body is to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, are ſprinkled with this water, for remiſſion of their ſins. And they further affirm, That no man can come to <hi>Mecha,</hi> whoſe viſit is not known to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who reveals the perſons to the Keepers there (all Eunuchs:) and if a Pilgrim come,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174907:21"/>a Raviſher, or wicked Man, a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, or any of Religion different from theirs; theſe ſaid Keepers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him entrance into <hi>Mecha.</hi> But the body of <hi>Mahomet</hi> is not there, as ſome affirm, but onely an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary form in the Wall of the Church, expreſſing the lineament of a body, which is often kiſſed; and ſo they return home again. Such lying follies, for miracles, theſe Infidels are poſſeſſed with, concerning <hi>Mahomet;</hi> and divers others, ſo ridiculous, as I omit for modeſties ſake: yet muſt adviſe the Reader, if he pleaſe, to interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate any Turk therein, and he will finde I have ſpoke nothing but meer Truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:174907:21"/>
               <head>Of their Alms.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Alcoran</hi> obligeth men to Alms, as meritorious, and much pleaſing God; and ſaith, <hi>The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry comes from the Devil.</hi> They have Hoſpitals for poor travellers, built by the Wills and Legacies of their Kings; where they have meat in different manners: ſome allow Rice with fleſh, others prepare Wheat Bread, and Water to drink; but for reſt or Lodgings, there is no place allowed: yet there are ſome few publick receptacles, where they are received without charge, or other bedding than Straw or Hay; but they repoſe under a good Roof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:174907:22"/>
               <head>Of their Sacrifice.</head>
               <p>THeir Offerings or Oblations are for the moſt part upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or vows, in ſickneſſes or other dangers; and then they kill an Ox or a Sheep, according to abilities; and promiſe to ſacrifice it in ſome certain place. This Offering is not burnt, or placed on an Altar, after the cuſtome of the <hi>Jews;</hi> but the beaſt being killed, the skin, head, and feet, and a fourth part of the fleſh, is given to the Prieſt; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother part, to the poor; a third, to neighbours; and the remainder they keep for themſelves and friends to rejoyce withal. Neither are they tied to perform theſe vows, unleſs they eſcape the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe or danger for which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them: all things with them being conditionall; <hi>I give you, if you give me.</hi> And the like is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174907:22"/>obſerved by the <hi>Greeks, Armenians,</hi> and other Aſiatick people, even of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Wills and Legacies.</head>
               <p>IF any of their Muſſelmen make a Will, their Legacies are given before Friends or Neighbours; and they are commonly for cutting Water-courſes, for conveying Springs from ſome remote places, to Hoſpitals, Churches, or dry ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations; and that for Piety ſake, and their ſouls benefit. Others give money to free bond-men out of thraldom. But Women for the moſt part (as moſt ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) bequeath their gifts to Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for a certain ſlaughter of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which they conceive to be greatly beneficial for their Souls. The Legacies of their Kings are for the building of Hoſpitals, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and ſo likewiſe are thoſe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and great perſonages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:174907:23"/>
               <head>Ceremonies of the Dead.</head>
               <p>VVHen any of their Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelmen die, men take the Funeral-care of men, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of women. They waſh the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted body very clean, and wrap it in fine linen; then they carry it out of Town, into ſome remote place, (for they hold it ſinful to bury in their Churches.) firſt, Friends of the deceaſed and Prieſts meet and go in progreſs, certain Monks bearing wax Candles; then follow ſome of their Prieſts ſinging till they come to the Grave, ſhaking their heads, &amp; often turning round, fall down with giddineſs, as in a trance. The better ſort have their Graves lined with Boards at bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom and at ſides, and covered with Boards, on which they throw the Earth, and ſtrowe ſometimes the ſeeds of Flowers thereon. Great
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174907:23"/>Men and Baſſa's have peculiar Chappels for themſelves and Kindred. The poor are buried by high-wayes, or in open-field. If the deceaſed be of poor ability, there is then money gathered for ſatisfaction of labour for thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Men, which is offered in the Streets.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the edifice of a Sepulchre, called <hi>Tulbe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OVer this ſtately Tombe, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prince-like) there is ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a goodly Temple, wherein their Kings are buried in the City with great magnificence. Both rich and meaner, have an Altar built of ſuch an heighth, as Beaſts cannot annoy or pollute it with any foulneſs: thither with lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; weepings they often return; and ſpread upon the monument ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of meats, bread, fleſh,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:174907:24"/>cheeſe, eggs, milk. This Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or Funeral-Supper continues for nine dayes after the parties burial, (according to the Heathen manner) for the ſoul of teh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted: and it is left to be eaten by the Poor, by Ants, or Fowls of the Air. They ſay, <hi>It equally pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God, to give alms to Beaſts that want, as men, when they are given for God's ſake.</hi> I have ſeen many buy birds in cages at good values, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſet them at liberty, and ſee them flye away; others, throw Bread into Rivers for Fiſhes, and that for the love of God, ſaying, That <hi>ſuch charity towards the needy, doth obtain a great reward from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:174907:24"/>
               <head>Concerning War.</head>
               <p>THe Turks have all one Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or King of the Race of <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> who hath next to himſelf in Authority two Sangiachs, or Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roys, chief Governours, th' one of <hi>Europe,</hi> th' other of <hi>Aſia;</hi> and theſe have under them Lieutenants of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer quality, who command the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Souldiery; and if they fail, being call'd to any expedition, are preſently puniſhed with death. He hath others always following him; as Councellors, Guardians of his body, ever neer him; chamberlains, chancellors, &amp; exactors of tribute, for monies and young people; with certain numbers of light-horſe, meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, &amp; divers others that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually follow the court. His greateſt ſtrength is in his Slaves; Children (for the moſt part) torn from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Parents, with Tribute-Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174907:25"/>bred and educated in ſeveral Seraglio's, Captives taken in War, and Renegado's. Of theſe, ſome are trained up, and ſerve on horſe; who have a double ſtipend to the Foot, and alwayes ready at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, in ſtables keeping four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred horſe together. The great body of Foot-Souldiery are the Janizaries, all commanded by a Chief, called their <hi>Aga,</hi> a perſon of mighty truſt, and like importance; who hath under him divers inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Commanders, and have Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio's apart. Of theſe, and Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liary Forces, the Turk can draw three hundred thouſand to the Field. A great part of theſe Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries attend the Court, Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors houſes, and protect all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Inhabitants and Travellers, for rewards; and are faithful in thoſe imployments. Their Standard in the Field, is an Horſe-Tail tied upon a pole; an Emblem of their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174907:25"/>firſt barbarity and rudeneſs. His ſtrength at Sea is not conſiderable, conſiſting moſt in Gallies, and thoſe not equal to ſome Italian Princes; nor hath he many, for want of Slaves, whom he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes more for Land-ſervices. The beſt of Shipping, is under the Baſſa's of <hi>Algier</hi> and <hi>Tunis,</hi> whom he manageth with much po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy; ſometime as Rebels, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time as good Subjects, to his beſt advantage againſt Chriſtians: for if they complain of loſs, the Turk then ſayes, <hi>He cannot rule them.</hi> If th' other do the like, he'll take tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble damages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Condition of Neblemen.</head>
               <p>THere is not any of thoſe great Perſonages that poſſeſs by right of inheritance any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, City or real Eſtate, to derive unto his Children or Succeſſors,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174907:26"/>without conſent of the King. If any of their Dukes or Princes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire poſſeſſions, it muſt be with this condition; the value of the Place or Territory is firſt conſidered, and the Revenues thereof, whereby the Turk apportioneth what number of Souldiers that can annually maintain: then the Lord is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned alwayes to keep in readineſs that number, for any his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and in default, his head is loſt: nothing can excuſe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in any commanded place, but known want of health and ſickneſs. And whenſoever it pleaſe the Turk to eaſe him of this benefit, it's at his liberty; but if not deprived, he enjoyes it during life: after death, if his Succeſſors will obſerve the fame conditions, they are often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; if not, 'tis then diſpoſed to others. And if it happen, any one of theſe great ones have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſpeak unto their King, with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:174907:26"/>eyes fixed on the ground, they dare not look him in the face.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Baſſa's, who may be called Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Chancellors, or Secretaries.</head>
               <p>THeſe for the moſt part are all Eunuchs, caſtrated when Youths, and bred in <hi>Seraglio's,</hi> for attendants on the Turkiſh Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines: and of later yeers, ſome of them (as I was informed, being a Slave to a great Man in <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>) are cut ſo cloſe the body, that they often die by th' inciſion; and if live, they ever after uſe ſmall pipes for diſcharging their water: ſuch is their cruel jealouſie, intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced (as 'twas ſaid) by an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour that perceived a Gelding leap a Mare. Theſe Baſſa's are of greateſt eſteem with the Turk, next to the Sangiachs; and they are almoſt all that are preferred to that dignity; Children of Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:174907:27"/>violently taken from them: and none of them, although he hath to Wife a Daughter of a Turk, (as <hi>Hurstan</hi> Baſſa had) can enjoy a Pariſh, Caſtle, or Village by inheritance; but if he be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted to any dignity or poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he enjoyes it till his death, or ſo long as the Turk pleaſeth. Each Baſſa hath a Court of Juſtice in the Province he commandeth, from whence appeals are to the King, or great Mufty; whoſe ſentence is concluding and immoveable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The obedience of Turks to the King.</head>
               <p>NOne of their Janizaries or great Captains have licenſe to wear Swords or other Arms within the Cities, unleſs the King go forth his Palace, for Devotion ſake or Hunting. And where there are Magiſtrates or Governours of Towns, Porters carry with them
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:174907:27"/>ſtaves or clubs; and finding any quarrellings or offerings at inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, they preſently puniſh them with thoſe inſtruments; and no man ſpeaking to them, dares look them in the face; but falling on the earth, kiſs their feet, with eyes to the ground, and ſpeak as to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And whenſoever they ſend forth Meſſengers with Letters to Governours, Cities, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, whoſe horſe grows faint by journeying, this Meſſenger hath full authority to diſ-horſe whom ere he meets; and meeting none, he turns into the next Town or Village, and repairs to the chief Officer; and if he preſently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides him not an horſe, he's hang'd before his door: and for this cauſe, many make uſe of aſſes, rather then keep horſe. And when this Meſſenger ſhall come to whom he was ſent, he is moſt honourably received, his Letters kiſſed with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174907:28"/>great humility, and their Contents anſwered with incredible celerity and quick diſpatch. No Princes dare contradict one ſillable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. None dare (as here) rebel; all men live in ſuch awful fear and trembling: Tortures and preſent death depending on his will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Turkiſh ſtrength, how diminiſhed.</head>
               <p>THe Emperour diſtributes in ſome equality all Provinces to his Noblemen; but with condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſuch a Souldiery ſhall be continually maintained by him with the Revenues of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, both in time of Peace and War. A Souldier killed, is not loſs to him, unleſs the Province likewiſe be loſt: as for example, The Turk hath now four hundred Souldiers, whereof one hundred is maintained by <hi>Hungary;</hi> now if he loſe <hi>Hungary,</hi> thoſe Souldiers
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:174907:28"/>are loſt: if he loſe no Province, he loſeth nothing; for he can raiſe more in their rooms; as Church-Officers, or benefits, eaſily finde in vancancies Succeſſors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The condition of Chazilars.</head>
               <p>THeſe are ſtout Souldiers, and excellently verſed in military affairs, who in their firſt encounters break their Lances, without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Armour, then a Sword, Lance, and Target, uſing it as we do with Coat of Fence and Helmet; the Lance being broke, they uſe the Sword, and fight valiantly, alwayes aiming at the head or hands, and think it ignominious to thurſt at their adverſary, or an horſe, with point of Sword. Theſe Men ſpend all their lives and hopes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of a Goddeſs, Fortune; having a Proverb with them, <hi>What is written, will befal them;</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:174907:29"/>that is, What that Goddeſs hath printed on the head at each Man's Nativity, cannot be poſſibly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, though he were preſerved in a Caſtle unexpugnable. The actions of theſe men are writ in verſes, and ſung by all Men; that others ſtirried up by like praiſe and honour, might, with like au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacity, advance againſt an Enemy, couragiouſly and valiantly: and, for each victory of theſe Men, their ſtipends are doubled; and, are obliged attendance on their King, on horſe-back, with Lances, Swords, and Iron Clubs: ſome, have Targets; ſome, none; and are paid as well in Peace as War.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The order of their Foot.</head>
               <p>THeir firſt are Bow-men, with Arrows, Bows, and Javelins; they are diſtinguiſhed from Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:174907:29"/>by coverings of the head. The ſecond is of Janizaries, who inſtead of Bows, have Guns, with ſhort Hatchets: all theſe are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from amongſt Chriſtians living under Tribute, by force ſnatched from their Friends being young, circumciſed, and educated as aforeſaid. Theſe fight moſt valiantly againſt Chriſtians, yet have but ſlender ſtipends for their maintenance; ſome four, five, or ſix Aſpers a day; of which, ſixty make a Crown Engliſh. And theſe are prohibited on pain of death, to come on horſe-back, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſick. There are ſome few likewiſe, ſons of Turks, made Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries. There is a third order, whom they call Azaplars, whoſe ſtipends determine with the War, and are all ſons of Turks. Theſe uſe a longer Lance, with Swords, and red hats or bonnets, or other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured cloath, with crooked angles
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:174907:30"/>like half Moons; and ſo diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Arms and Habit, from th' o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther orders. There is a fourth of the Grecian ſect, who have no other ſtipend, then freedom from paying Tributes and Tenths. They commonly attend the Turks horſe of pleaſure, keeping them at their own charge, and well managing them for war.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Turks Pavilions.</head>
               <p>WHen the King removes from <hi>Constantinople,</hi> to any Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of War, he carrieth with him double Tents, that when one is planted this day, th' other is carried to the next ſtation, ready to receive him the day following: the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and magnitude of theſe Pavili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is ſuch, that afar off they ſeem no leſs then Cities: round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the King's Pavilion, are the Tents of Princes and great Men,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:174907:30"/>encompaſſing his in circle. Then the horſe-men of Arms, two or three together, have their Tent: the foot-men have the like for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline ſake, and to keep them from cold Air. When the body of the Army moves, Yeomen foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men clear the wayes, and here and there make heaps of ſtone, or piles of wood, for eaſe and direction of the paſſage; ſo as even in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the night they can hardly erre. The Army moveth at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, and till mid-day following marcheth. The King rides be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Baſſa's talking with him, before whom marcheth ſome of the order of Janizaries on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, bearing lighted Candles in time of night. Certain Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains follow them with iron Clubs round pointed, who keep off men from ſight of the King a good large diſtance: amongſt theſe, are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the King's Guard; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:174907:31"/>them, a Chariot of Women and Boyes, fitted for uſe of the Turk and his Nobility. Theſe great Men, go ſome before, ſome follow theſe Captains with great multitudes of Souldiers, horſe and foot, and all conditions; ſome for ſtipend, ſome for plunder; but all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Their carriages of Beaſts.</head>
               <p>THen follow a multitude of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels, Mules, Horſe, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Elephants laden with Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, Pavilions, and all neceſſaries for military uſes; and where the Turk pitcheth his Tent, there eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, according to his condition, (as in a City) ſets up his habitation; Boothes for Taylors, Bakers, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, Sutlers, and all ſorts of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuallers: ſome ſell dainty fleſh, and fowls; and when freſh meat cannot be had, then what is brought
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:174907:31"/>upon their Beaſts, they expoſe to ſale; bisket, dry meats, cheeſe, curds, and milk. All Turks are generally moſt patient in ſuffering hunger, thirſt, and cold. They ſeldom lodge in Towns, but field it in their Tents, neer water-ſprings, Rivers, or Meadows, taking more care of their cattel then themſelves; content with little and courſe diet, curds mingled with water, bread with milk, ſometime bisket: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and ſervant eat together. They keep deep ſilence in the night; they neglect ſtirring after fugitives, for fear of raiſing clamours; which are forbid upon great mulcts and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments: but when they go to reſt, or riſe to march, all with an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous noiſe, cry out, <hi>Allah, Allah, Allohu,</hi> that is, <hi>O God,</hi> thrice repeated.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:174907:32"/>
               <head>Of justice exerciſed in War.</head>
               <p>THere is ſo much ſeverity in military diſcipline, that no Souldier dares unjuſtly ſeize on any thing of anothers; for if he do, he dies without mercy. They have amongſt them certain Guardians, Defenders of all Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers from Souldiers violence, with Boyes of eight or ten yeers old, carrying bread, eggs, fruit, oats, and ſuch-like things to ſell. Theſe Guardians are bound to free and preſerve all Orchards, Gardens, Cloſes, they paſs by; ſo far, that they themſelves dare not touch an Apple, Pear, or Grape, or any ſuch-like thing, without the owners licenſe; otherwiſe they loſe their heads. When I was preſent in the Turkiſh Army in an Expedition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Perſian,</hi> I ſaw a great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders head, with horſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:174907:32"/>all three cut off, becauſe that horſe had been found grazing in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans paſture unſatisfied for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Celebrations of a Turkiſh victory.</head>
               <p>WHen a Conqueſt is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the Cities ſtraight throw themſelves into all delights and joyings. At en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of night, for good auſpice of the ſolemnity, Torches, Wax-can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, Lamps, Fire-brands, Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works, and all things that give light, are everywhere diſpoſed of throughout the City; with Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, coſtly Hangings, Tapeſtry, and Silken, Silver, and Gold Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, their houſes all are covered, but eſpecially that way, by which the Emperor entreth. The chiefeſt triumph is made in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> his conftant reſidence, unleſs occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by war into ſome other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And he is bound by Law
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:174907:33"/>at every three yeers end, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſome expedition into Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Territories, for advancing or defending his own Kingdom. I verily believe, and do confeſs, for thoſe dayes he celebrates for Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, no Mortal eye, (nay, not the Moon or Sun) did ere behold a ſpectacle more glorious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent, for order, number, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, richneſs, ſtate, and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in all kindes. It is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for onely man to be exalted to a loftier degree of ſublimation, then this Pagan when triumphful.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their hunting and hawking.</head>
               <p>NO Nation under the Sun de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights ſo much in hunting, as doth the <hi>Turkiſh;</hi> they'll follow game through rocky, ſteepy, craggy mountains, and that, on horſeback, taking diverſities of Beaſts; but if any chance to be killed, or ſuffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:174907:33"/>by dogs or chaſe, they never eat thereof, nor any Chriſtian that lives in thoſe Regions: and if they kill wilde Boars, they give them to the next inhabiting Chriſtians, <hi>Muſſelmen</hi> being forbidden to feed on Hogs fleſh. The Turk hath multitudes of Faulkoners (above thouſands) in conſtant wages through his Empire. Their Hawks both long and ſhort wing'd very hardy. The like charge he's at, for all ſorts of dogs: nothing can move in th'Air, or ſtir on Land, that ſhall not be encountred, and ſeized on. Theſe charges, with the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery, Officers, <hi>Seraglio's,</hi> and Court-attendances, are in a manner infinite; and yet ſupplied more by caſualities then Revenues conſtant: for he commands all mens fortunes at his pleaſure, and is the general Heir of all that by nature die, or violence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:174907:34"/>
               <head>Of Artificers and Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bandmen.</head>
               <p>THe Country-people with their Servants plow their Lands, and pay the Tenths of all encreaſe unto the King. Artificers main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain themſelves by Trades: who live in idleneſs, conſume in hunger. They eagerly purſue all ſorts of Merchandizings; travelling the leſſer <hi>Aſia, Arabia, Aegypt,</hi> and States of the <hi>Venetians.</hi> They have their Baths in every City, where in ſolemn manner they waſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. When they make Water, they waſh that part; and the like, when they eaſe their bodies. The like is done by Women, who have hand-maids following them, with Veſſels filled with Water; and when they bathe, they anoynt themſelves with ſuch an unguent, that within the ſpace of half an hour, roots off all hair from parts
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:174907:34"/>anoynted. Men and Women do the ſame; not ſuffering hair to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: and this is done twice or thrice each month, eſpecially when they frequent the Church; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, (as violators of ſacred places) they are burnt with fire. They have divers ſorts of Artificers; Taylors, Shoe-makers, Gold and Silver-Smiths, and for all ſorts of Metals; Painters, Carpenters, Stone-cutters; but not of ſuch wits and exquiſite inventions, as in our parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Juſtice among Citizens.</head>
               <p>THey have one Judge as well of Chriſtians as Turks, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes choſen from amongſt the <hi>Muſſelmen</hi>) to adminiſter equal right to all men. If any kill another, he ſuffereth death: if ſteal or violently taketh from another, he is hanged; as it happened to a Janizary, who
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:174907:35"/>drunk milk of a poor Woman's, brought to ſell, and paid not for it; and accuſed before the Judge, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the fact; whereupon, being ſtrerched up by cords at his feet, and about his middle, he forth with vomited the milk, and was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by the Judge commanded to be ſtrangled: this happened: in my preſence at <hi>Damaſco,</hi> when I traveled from <hi>Armenia</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> If any commit adultery, the Man is caſt into ſtrict Priſon; yet after divers months may be redeemed: the Woman is carried about the ſtreets riding on an Aſs, beaten naked with whips, ſtones thrown at her, and a Bull's pizzle tied about her Neck. He that gives a blow, is cut croſs the face, and led about the ſtreets for terrour. All ſuits have this good piece of Juſtice, that right or wrong they laſt not above three dayes. Their differences are few, becauſe they buy and ſell
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:174907:35"/>for ready Money; their chiefeſt wealth conſiſting in it: for few have Lands or Revenues, but who command the Souldiery: but generally the Turk 's Law and Equity is in his Sword, and both opppreſſed and ſtifled with Fear and Bribery, two potent and prevailing Agents. To ſpoil, to rob, to kill, to murther, upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of intereſt, he ſayes, <hi>'Tis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice;</hi> devaſtation and deſtruction of whole Provinces &amp; Kingdoms, he calleth, <hi>Peace.</hi> And if in ought he adviſe with Counſel or the great Mufty, 'tis not for ſubſtance, but formality of juſtice, as well aſſured from gain-ſaying an oppoſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Husbandry.</head>
               <p>BOth Chriſtians and <hi>Muſſelmen</hi> manure and till their Grounds, Vineyards, and Paſtures, and have like Fruits and Corn to ours;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:174907:36"/>Wheat, Millet, Barley, Oats, win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Wheat, Peaſe, Beans, and all kindes of Pulſe, and Rice in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; Linen, and Cotten wools, more then theſe Nations; Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards like ours; but uſe their Grapes in different manner; where we make Wine, the Turk hath a kinde of Honey with them; ſo medicining their Grapes, that both in taſte and colour they appear al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes freſh: other Fruits they have in great plenty; Melons, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers, Pumpions: repleniſh well their Fields and Gardens in their ſeaſons: Nuts, Pears, Apples, Peaches of all ſorts, Apricocks, Cheſnuts, Figs, Lemons, Oringes, Cherries, and ſuch-like, at ſmall rates; but not in equal plenty in all Kingdomes: and there are ſome within the Turks Dominion, as <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> and leſs <hi>Armenia,</hi> where, in regard of cold, they have no ſuch-like Frutages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:174907:36"/>
               <head>Of diverſity of Cattle.</head>
               <p>THey have Shepherds, (whom they call <hi>Sobanlars</hi>) alwayes living in ſolitary places, and every Month remove their ſtations; they neither have poſſeſſions or houſes, other then their Tents, and Cattle; as Camels, Mules, Horſe, Cows, Oxen, Sheep, and Goates; whom they feed, make Cheeſe and Butter; ſhear the Wool, and ſo make Cloaks, Mantles, and Tapeſtry, which they ſell, and ſupply thereby their Families with Corn and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries. All theſe Shepherds pay the King tenths of all annual en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll Chriſtians further pay Tribute, that live under the Turkiſh Government, for every Male, one Crown yearly; and, that which is moſt cruel, their ſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maried, are taken forcibly from them every fifth yeer, when their Tents are viſited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:174907:37"/>
               <head>Of Houſes.</head>
               <p>THey have no great magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of buildings; moſt of them are of bricks, but differing; ſome are burn'd in Furnaces, ſome dryed by the Sun. Their houſes are contiguous, like ours in <hi>Europe;</hi> but in <hi>Natolia,</hi> they are flat tabled without elevation; from whence by Gutters, Pipes, and Chanels, Rain-water flows down to them. The houſes lowe; none above two ſtories, and meanly furniſhed, if not poorly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Garments.</head>
               <p>THeir Veſtments are made of Wool, Flax, and ſpun Silk, ſufficiently magnificent. They uſe a Garment (which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Chaucan</hi>) ſtraight, full of plaits, and of length even to their ankles;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:174907:37"/>abhorring breeches, as too much directing to, and expreſſing privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Their ſhirts or ſmocks are dyed in colour Violet. Their heads are covered with great rolls of Callico, or ſuch-like ſtuffe, wound about in faſhion of Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mids; which they call <hi>Turbants.</hi> Women of quality go alwayes with their faces veiled; which are never ſeen of ſtrangers, or in publick places. Their ſhooes are high, with ſtrong ſoles, for longer ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice both of men and women. Some ſay that <hi>Mahomet</hi> had a bald or ſcalded head, which he covered with white linen rolled up, as their <hi>Turbants,</hi> from thence derived, and ſtill continued, for they never alter faſhions. They wear long beards, as tokens of their freedom, all Slaves being ſhaved. No great difference in habit between rich and poor; but in the ſtuffes. They are religiouſly cleanly, and never
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:174907:38"/>ſeen to unburden nature, but always after waſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Viands.</head>
               <p>THey uſe, as we, bread white and courſe, which they ſprinkle with certain ſeeds before 'tis baked, and yieldeth a great ſweetneſs to the eater; which with us is onely uſed in <hi>Granada,</hi> and about <hi>Sivilia</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi> They uſe much art and ſauces in their Cookeries: but ordinary food is pulſe of Rice, ſo thickned, that it muſt be parted with the hands: they feed on all fleſh but Hoggs. There are no Taverns or Innes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; yet in the ſtreets, divers ſorts of victuals are ſold, and all things neceſſary for man's ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:174907:38"/>
               <head>Of their Beverage.</head>
               <p>THey have three ſorts of drinks: the firſt made with Sugar and Honey mingled with Water. The ſecond of Raiſins, the ſtones taken out, and boyled in Water, whereto they add ſome Roſe-water, and a little perfect Honey; and this is to be ſold in moſt parts thorow <hi>Turky;</hi> for it is ſweet, and puffeth up the belly. The third is made of a Fruit (called <hi>Pechmez</hi>) into Muſt, and hath a kinde of Honey-taſte and colour with it; this, mingled with Water, is given to their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. The Houſes where they ſell, are frequented as Oſteries in <hi>Italy,</hi> or Taverns with us. Turks for the moſt part drink onely Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; they are not ſuffered to buy or ſwallow Wines; and who hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to be accuſed, and proved to have drunken thereof, his teſtimony
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:174907:39"/>in all occaſions and actions in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid: and yet in private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian houſes, they do not abſtain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their manner of eating.</head>
               <p>WHen they go to Dinner, they firſt ſtrow Mattreſſes on the floor, and ſpread upon them Carpets or Pillows; ſome ſit on the bare ground. Their Tables are made of skins, and plaited, to be drawn open more or leſs, like to a budget. They neither ſit, as we do, nor lie along on elbowes, as the ancients; but like a croſs of <hi>Burgondy,</hi> with leggs infolded, they ſit Taylor-wiſe. They alwayes Pray before they eat, then eat greedily and haſtily, but with deep ſilence; and in that time their Wives ſecluded from them. Men-ſervants after twelve yeers age, are never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to co-habitate in houſes where Women are; but under ſuch age,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:174907:39"/>they go about the houſes, ſerving their Maſter's occaſions. Captive women have never liberty to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, unleſs their Miſtreſſes or Ladies go to Vineyards, Graves of Friends departed, Baths, or Gardens out of Town (which they often do) for recreation ſake; and otherwiſe are kept ſtrict at work in houſes, not ſuffered to converſe with other captive Servants; as ſhall be more at large declared in the following Chapter. Their diſhes are commonly placed at ſuch diſtance one over another, as 'twere on Pillars, that each man may make choice of three, which pleaſeth beſt. They eat three times a day; but quick therein, unleſs at a Feaſt, where they ſit all day.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:174907:40"/>
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the afflictions of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and Chriſtians un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Turkiſh Tribute.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the King of <hi>Turks</hi> makes Expeditions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſtians, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt divers ſorts of Merchants, there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way follow him on Camels, a mighty number of Buyers or Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Children or Men, who in hope of getting Slaves, carry with them bundles of long Ropes, wherewith they eaſily tye together
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:174907:40"/>fifty or ſixty men. Theſe traders purchaſe of the Souldiery or Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booters, whomſoever the Sword hath not devoured; which is granted them, upon condition that the King may have the tenth of what is traffick'd for, the reſt unto themſelves to ſell. Nor is there any Merchandize ſo profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amongſt them, nor ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent; as anciently among the <hi>Romans,</hi> who called things fairly bought, their proper Goods and Rights, as juſt as that of Slaves.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the Turks imploy their ſlaves.</head>
               <p>THe youth and aged of both Sexes, whom Chance by tenths appropriates to the <hi>Turk,</hi> he thus diſpoſeth; the elder in yeers he ſells for Husband-men, who yet are rarely or cheap bought; for they ſeldom eſcape the Sword; their age making them leſs vendible.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:174907:41"/>Young men and Maidens, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine them in <hi>Seraglio's,</hi> there to be inſtructed in uſeful Arts for future times. But firſt, they muſt deny their Faith in Chriſt, and then be circumcifed. And thus initiated in their Ceremonies, they diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examine their phyſiognomies, and the ſeveral lineaments of their bodies, and then the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure; and according to conceived ſtrength, forwardneſs of wit, and diſpoſitions, they are deſtinated to learn Laws of the Country, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of Wars; and in the mean time are allowed a dayly ſtipend of two or three Aſpers, ſixty whereof make five ſhillings, which they conceive a liberal ſufficiency for diet and clothing, until they are fitted for imployments. In the elements of War, they thus are trained, according to each ſtrength: they firſt have given them a light bow; skill and ſtrength in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:174907:41"/>they have a greater and a heavier; ſo by degrees they are fitted for expedition. They have Inſtructors, ſevere Exactors of their dayly Exerciſes; and when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they erre much from the mark, ſo often are they cruelly whip'd with ſcourges. Theſe are inrolled in the order of Bow-men. Others are inſtructed and made fit for Janizaries, who have appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Maſters and Teachers every day to fight, two together with Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Others (an horrid thing) who have more lovely faces, are ſo cloſe cut, that nothing like Man is left them; and this not done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great and eminent danger to life: and if the party eſcape death, his health is for no other uſe, but their moſt wicked luſts; and after youth's grown aged, they are put to the offices of Eunuchs, to attend on Ladies, Concubines, Horſes, Mules, and ſome Kitchin-imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:174907:42"/>
               <head>The condition of Virgins and other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</head>
               <p>SUch as are of extraordinary beauty, comelineſs, or compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of body, are choſen out for Concubines; mean and indifferent Faces, are appointed Matrons, hand-maids; amongſt whoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices ſome are ſo filthy, and ſo loathſome, as were before (though ſomewhat uncivilly) related. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are ſet to womens work, as ſpinning, carding, weaving. It is free for none of them to profeſs the Chriſtian Faith, or hope of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty during life. There is ſome content in hope, but theſe have none.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:174907:42"/>
               <head>How private Turks uſe Priſoners.</head>
               <p>HItherto hath been ſpoken how the Kings uſe Captives; now how private men their Priſoners newly taken: firſt, they threaten them with all ſorts of meancing ſharp words, promiſes, and allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to entice them to Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; which if yeilded to, they are treated ſomewhat more courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; but then all hope of ever returning to their Country is clean cut off; and whoſoever endeavours it, burning is his appointed puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Such as are thought more firm and leſs fugitive, are admitted to their Maſters Military imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and can onely be made free, when age hath made them uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; and then he is rather turned off, then remitted orderly; or when the Maſter by hurt in War, or danger of death, bequeaths him
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:174907:43"/>liberty. They are permitted marriage; but their Children are diſpoſed at the Maſter's pleaſure; which makes the more underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſort utterly abhor marriage. They who refuſe Circumciſion, are miſerably and unhumanely treated; of which I have had the experience of thirteen yeers ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings: nor can I expreſs in words the great calamities of ſuch people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Christians ignorant in mechanick Arts are uſed.</head>
               <p>THe condition of ſuch unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men is wretched. Thoſe whoſe toyl brings profit, are onely in reputation with them: and therefore learned Men, Prieſts, and Noble men, who have lived in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiredneſs and pleaſures, when they fall into the hands of <hi>Turks,</hi> are of all moſt miſerable; the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:174907:43"/>or Manſcourſer beſtows no coſt on them, as ſcant vendible; they walk with naked head and feet, and often their whole bodies; no new cloaths ſucceed, the old worn out; they are hurried through Mountains, Rocks, from place to place, Winter and Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and have no end thereof till death, or that they finde a fooliſh Purchaſer, that (they think) buyes ill Merchandize; but no man is ſo happy, or eſteem'd amongſt them, for Age, Art or Beauty, that they being ſick will leave behinde them. Firſt, they are whipped to go on; if they cannot do that, then they are put on horſeback; and there not able to ſit upright, their bellies are tied on horſeback, no otherwiſe then a ſack of Corn or Cloak-bag; if he die, he's ſtrip'd of all cloaths, and thrown into the next ditch, to be devoured by dogs and vultures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:174907:44"/>
               <head>How Priſoners newly taken are uſed.</head>
               <p>THey do not onely binde them in endleſs chains, but, in their journey, alſo manacle their hands; they march the diſtance of a large pace one from another, that mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally they do no hurt; and tye their hands, leſt with ſtones they miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief do their Maſters: that when ſometimes they lead great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, as ten times five hundred chain'd together, the ſtrength of whom, if hands at liberty to throw ſtones, might much annoy them. At night when they reſt, their feet are likewiſe chained, and expoſed to all injuries of weather. The condition of Women is a little more humane; they who have ſtrength of limbs, are driven on foot; thoſe more tender, are ſet on horſes; ſuch as are infirm and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ride, are put in baskets or ripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:174907:44"/>as we uſe geeſe. Afterwards their condition is ſadder; either they are included in ſtrong Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets, or forced to endure the wicked luſts of their Merchants. Where ſtill they are, is ever heard vaſt and hideous howlings of both ſexes, ſuffering violations from them; neither doth the age of leaven or ſix yeers, defend them from thoſe vitious actions: a people incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable wicked, both againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and before libidinous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How uſed that are expoſed to ſale.</head>
               <p>AT the break of day they are brought to Market, like droves of ſheep, or herds of goats: Merchants appear, prizes are ſet; if the priſoner be liked, his cloaths are ſtripped off, he is viewed by the buyer, all members ſuveyed, tryed and throughly ſearched for faults in joynts or arteries; if he
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:174907:45"/>pleaſe not, then returned to the owner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this is done until he finde a purchaſer. When bought, he's carried to ſome heavy ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to plow, keep ſheep; omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing baſer Offices. They endure there many unheard examples of calamities: I have ſeen men tyed together with yokes, to draw the plow. Maidens are ſeverely forced to perpetual labours; ſeparated from the ſight of men, nor are they ſuffered ſpeech or conference with other Servants. If any man be taken Priſoner with wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, him ſome great perſon wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly purchaſeth, to be imployed in his Country-houſe, in Tillage, Vineyards, Meadows, Paſtures; and Children born of them, are all his Slaves: and if they perſevere in Chriſtian Faith, a certain time is alotted them to ſervitude, and then made free; their Children notwithſtanding continue Slaves
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:174907:45"/>at the Maſter's will, and imployed where he pleaſeth; for they have no certain nor enrolled Eſtates of Lands, and ſo no aſſured ſeats of reſidence. If after making free, they deſire to return to their Country, they have Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents given for their Journey. But to ſuch as abjure the Chriſtian Religion, no certain time of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage is preſcribed them, nor right of return; all hopes of their liberty, totally depends upon the Maſter's pleaſure: and when they have got freedom, they pay the Tenths, as other Turks, but freed from other Taxes with which Chriſtians are burthened.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Captives made Shepherds.</head>
               <p>THe Husband — man hath an hard and ſad condition, but the Shepherd far more grievous; they always live in ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:174907:46"/>night and day, covered onely with the roof of heaven. The Maſter and the Wife have ſome ſmall Tents; no ſhelter for the Shepherd, unleſs at ſpare times compelled to work on Tapeſtry or Carpets. Every month they change their Paſtures, and drive their flocks from one Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to another. Some Maſters that have more humanity, now and then give ſmall rewards, which the Servant keeps as his proper Goods, and preſerves, to bear the charge of a return to his Country, if ever he get liberty; but theſe largeſſes are ſeldom done, and then, but as a miſerable enticement to ſervitude, thinking thereby to withdraw their hopes of ſhifting from them. To ſuch as deny Chriſt, and are circumciſed, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they dare not run away, no like indulgence offered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:174907:46"/>
               <head>Eſcapes of priſoners out of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>European</hi> Slaves may more eaſily eſcape, then thoſe ſold into tranſmaritime Regions; they paſs Rivers onely, that may be ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med over; others, with great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty muſt paſs the Helleſpont. Such as intend eſcapes, uſually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it in Harveſt ſeaſon, to hide themſelves in Fields of Corn, and by it live. The Nights they Travel; the Day lie cloſe, in Corn, Woods, or Marſhes; and rather chuſe to be devoured by Wolves, then brought back to their Tyger-Maſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Out of leſſer <hi>Aſia.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHo flye from thence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to the Helleſpontick Sea, between <hi>Callipolis,</hi> and thoſe Towers of <hi>Sestos</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidos,</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:174907:47"/>now called by the Turks, <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaz Aſer,</hi> that is, <hi>Castles on the mouth of the Sea,</hi> where the Waters are ſtraight and narrow; hither they come with Saws and Ropes, cut Timber-Trees, and tye them faſt together, to ſerve and ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for ſhipping; carrying no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with them but ſalt. If Winde and Fortune favour, in three or four hours they are wafted over; if otherwiſe, they periſh in the Sea, or reforc'd again upon the Coaſt of <hi>Aſia;</hi> if ſafely paſs, they then betake themſelves to the Mountains, and by inſpection of the Pole and the Star <hi>Bootes,</hi> they tend their way North-ward; and ſuſtain themſelves with Acorns and Herbs ſod in ſalt. If many flie together in ſociety, ſometimes in Night, they ſet upon the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, and what they finde of Victuals take from them; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time they kill, and are ſometime
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:174907:47"/>killed, or taken, and returned to their old Maſters and Drudgeries: but the ſeveral dangers of travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, conſumes more then eſcape, by ſhipwrack, the enemies ſword, wilde beaſts, and ſtarving hunger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The puniſhment of Fugitives.</head>
               <p>SOme are hanged up by the heels, and moſt cruelly ſcourged; and if commit murther, the ſoles of his feet are all ſlaſhed into furrows, and ſalt ſtuffed in. Some have great iron Chains, faſtned on their necks, and forced to wear them day and night, and as long as the Maſter pleaſeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The charity of Greeks and Armenians to Captives.</head>
               <p>DEath, and confiſcation of all ſorts of Goods, is inflicted on thoſe who undertake, procure, or
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:174907:48"/>aſſiſt Captives in their flight, or running away; yet notwithſtanding both <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Armenians</hi> ceaſe not to entertain them, being Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to hide them, and in diſguiſes to conduct them unto ſhippings of the Venetians or other Chriſtians, and freely give them good proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and all things neceſſary for their journeys; nor do they ſpare or omit any kinde of piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; for they confeſs to have had heard the like experience from Chriſtians charity, when as they travel for conſcience ſake to <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Compostella.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Incantation of Turks against Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitives.</head>
               <p>THey have certain kinde of Charms, which they think can draw them off from flying. The name of the Slave is written in a Schedule of Paper, which is
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:174907:48"/>hung up in his Tent or Houſe: then with vengeable and horrible Curſes, his head is charged and threatned, conceiving this by the Devil's help, the Fugitive will be affrighted with meeting of Lyons and Dragons in his Journey, or that the Seas or Rivers will ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, the heavens will grow dark, and theſe aſtoniſhments will bring him back again.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The memory of Chriſt by degrees loſt in former Chriſtian Provinces.</head>
               <p>THere is ſome memory yet left of the expugnation of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> the Kingdoms of <hi>Greece, Albania, Valachia,</hi> and <hi>Servia,</hi> now reduced to Provinces. Theſe, for a long time, conſtantly retained the Chriſtian Faith, but their Children have forgot it; and there will come to paſs a full ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion of Chriſt. And likely it
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:174907:49"/>is to fall out ſo in <hi>Croatia, Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Sclavonia,</hi> which are now ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments and adjuncts to the Turkiſh Empire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The condition of the conquered.</head>
               <p>VVHen a Province is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued and taken, all ſorts of Goods moveable and immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are given away for ſpoyle. They totally extirpate the whole Nobility; but eſpecially the Princely Iſſue. And when they took <hi>John</hi> the King's Son of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> and favoured him with life, it was on good advice, that if <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> were loſt again, they might imploy and involve him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any new incumbrances; and when the Province ſhould be in a quiet and calme condition, then to diſpatch him: for in ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, the Turk regards neither Kindred, Father or Brother; he
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:174907:49"/>ſpares none. And if they do kill and murder not all Church and Clergy-men they take; yet they expoſe them to all ſcorn, naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and beggery, deſpoyling them of all their Fortunes, Goods, and Dignities. Their Bells, their Organs, and other Inſtruments and Ornaments of Churches, Chappels, and Devotions, they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and tear from the Temples, profaning them with conſecration to their <hi>Mahomet;</hi> leaving onely the moſt miſerable and wretched Chappels to the Chriſtians, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are forbid publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and may pray ſeemingly in ſilence: which Chappels, when either Earth-quake, Fire. Tempeſt, or Age deſtroy, they muſt in no ſort re-edifie. Preaching or reading parts of the Scripture is utterly forbidden. It is a ſin to admit a Chriſtian to any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Office, to wear, have Arms
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:174907:50"/>or habit like a Turk: or elſe to uſe the recreations of cheerfulneſs, as Pageants, Playes, or Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings. If they injure Chriſt or you, with bitter or contumaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous words, you muſt be ſilent, and endure it. If you ſpeak ought againſt their profeſſed Religion. you are forced to circumciſion; and but to whiſper again <hi>Mahomet,</hi> Fire and Brimſtone followeth. If a Chriſtian on horſeback paſs by a <hi>Muſſelman,</hi> (that is, one initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in the Turkiſh Faith) he muſt, on neceſſity, light from his horſe, and bowing downe his head worſhip him; which if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, he ſtraight is knocked down with clubs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:174907:50"/>
               <head>The condition of Prieſts and Fryers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Tribute.</head>
               <p>THey are held the worſt of Men, and are eſteemed by Turks the very Sacriledge and Scandal of God and Mankinde. They have no benefit from Churches. Upon ſome feſtival dayes, a little bread is given them by poor Women, and not on other dayes. They get their livelihood by carrying Wood; their cuſtome being, to cut down ſticks in Woods, lade them on Aſſes; and with this Merchandize, they cry about the Streets, <hi>Wood to be ſold.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:174907:51"/>
               <head>The Tribute of Chriſtians.</head>
               <p>THey pay a part of all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, not onely of Corn and Cattle, but even Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks pay it out of all their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits. And then they pay another ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie, for every ſingle man through a Family, each head a Crown. If Parents refuſe this Tribute, their Children are taken from them, and made Slaves. Others are bound in Chains, and beg from door to door to pay this Crown; which if they cannot this way pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, they are caſt into perpetual Priſon; and when all Duties are performed, it is yet lawful for the Turk to chuſe the beſt amongſt his Children, whom he circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeth, and removes from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach or ſight of Parents, and breeds him for his Wars, ne'er to return to Friends; and ſo a childe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:174907:51"/>eaſily forgets both Chriſt, his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and his Kindred; that after, if he chance in company with them, he ſhall not know them. No Man can expreſs by Words, the Lamentations, Cries, Tears and grievous ſighs, at this diſtraction of Children. The Father to ſee his Son (educated in the fear of Chriſt) torn from him, and made an Inſtrument of Satan, to oppoſe Chriſt: hurried from his Mother, to live perpetually with ſtrangers, leaving whatſoever is dear in blood, pleaſing in ſociety, or loving in familiarity, with an everlaſting dereliction: after liſted in the ranks of thoſe the <hi>Greeks</hi> call Fatherleſs and Motherleſs; yet many of theſe although they have denied Chriſt, carry about them the Goſpel of St. <hi>John, (In the beginning was the word,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>Greek</hi> or the <hi>Arabick</hi> tongue) as an amulet or preſervative in their Armpits; and with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:174907:52"/>they expect the Chriſtian Sword (according to ſome Turkiſh propheſies) ſhould revenge and free them from thoſe great afflictions and perſecutions; and that if Chriſtians do it not, whatever is the cauſe, or with what mindes ſoever hindred; all very ill deſerve of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:174907:52"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>A Narration of a diſpute with a</hi> TURK.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had travelled with much labour and many dangers the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter parts of the world, and ſeen many plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Towns &amp; Countrys, as <hi>Socrates, Plato,</hi> &amp; other Philoſophers had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently done; at length I arrived at the famous City of <hi>Hungary, Vara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinum,</hi> where by chance I met one <hi>Dervis Gſielebi,</hi> a skilful man in the Laws of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> who having diſpatched his buſineſs with the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:174907:53"/>Governour, he very much deſired conference with ſome Chriſtian a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion on either ſide. This motion of his being publiſhed by an Interpreter, and none for divers dayes appearing to encounter him, in defence of the Chriſtian cauſe, though many religious perſons were in that Town, (ſtruck mute and ſpeechleſs at the courage of one Ethnick Infidel) who ſeemed to me like <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that durſt not adventure on one uncircumciſed <hi>Goliah,</hi> provoking them. This I perceiving, and grieving in my ſpirit, that in ſuch plenty of Clerks and learned men, none was ſo well armed with Truth, as durſt (though by Interpreters) reprove the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of ſuch an Heathen; And fearing that ſo wicked and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a ſilence, in ſo good a Cauſe, with ſo bad a Man, would betray the Truth, and render our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt's Opinion with him
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:174907:53"/>more ignominious; I my ſelf, though never called to Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Function, undertook the charge of arguing this point of Piety with him; and ſo a prefixed day was agreed on between us: when multitudes of people of each Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, came Spectators of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. The place was in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of <hi>Franciſcans;</hi> the day, <hi>Whitſon</hi>-Sunday, day of Pentecoſt; where he moved to me firſt this Queſtion: <hi>Where God had his being, before the Heavens and Earth, and therein all things elſe were created?</hi> Which Queſtion, though it ſeemed to me not much pertinent to our purpoſe, yet leſt he ſhould imagine us ignorant of our great God's uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal preſence, I ſaid, He then was in his own being. But when that ſeemed to him ſomewhat ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and that he did not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently underſtand it, I then told him, He was where he now is. Which
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:174907:54"/>he underſtanding, denied in the general, and ſaid, <hi>Not ſo; but that he then was in a bright cloud.</hi> Which, when he earneſtly affirmed, I quoted <hi>Geneſis;</hi> (for they alſo read the books of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) and ſaid, If God were in a Cloud, before the Foundation of Heaven and Earth, then that Cloud muſt be created before them both: and upon further argument on this point, being at laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, he would diſpute no further in it; but gave me leave to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſome Queſtion to him; and for ſolemnity of that dayes ſake, I thought fit to ſay ſomething there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and finding theſe words <hi>(In the name of God, his mercies, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of them)</hi> in their <hi>Alcoran,</hi> in the <hi>Arabian</hi> Tongue and Character, I deſired him to read them: The myſtery of the holy Trinity. Which when he had conſidered, and wondred at, he ſaid, <hi>Christian,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:174907:54"/>from whence had you this? for in the beginning of all our actions, we</hi> Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelmen <hi>uſe theſe three words, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix them to every Chapter of our</hi> Alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran; <hi>when we ſit down to eat, when we go to prayers, when we waſh our hands, or other parts of our bodies, theſe words we first pronounce; and theſe actions finiſhed, we ſprinkle our heads with water, and repeat theſe words,</hi> In the Name of God, his Mercies, and the Spirit of them. When thus he had confeſſed the Truth, I deſired to underſtand from him what he meant by the word <hi>Mercies:</hi> who replied, <hi>He under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it literally, without other ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> Then I applied my ſelf to the myſtical Interpretation, and divided it according to Truth into three Perſons, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, and ſhewed them written in the <hi>Arabick</hi> tongue. And when he ſaw I had mentioned the Son of God, he queſtion'd, <hi>How
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:174907:55"/>God could have a Son? ſince according to their Law and Doctrine of Mahomet, God had neither Wife nor Childe.</hi> To whom I anſwered, according to my weak underſtanding and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; We Chriſtians call God the Father, for his Creatures ſake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt creating Cauſe, and ſole Preſerver of all created, who was for ever in the ſame Eſſence he now is in, and will be for Eternity; and is the firſt Perſon in the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. We believe the Son, (who by <hi>Mahemet</hi> in the <hi>Arabick</hi> phraſe is called <hi>Rahman,</hi> and ſignifieth <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> ſo changed by him) to be likewiſe God, not according to fleſh (for God is a Spirit) born of a Woman; but of the Eſſence and ſubſtance of God Omnipotent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by God the Father, to put away the ſins of the World, and ſo took humane fleſh, by the Holy Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> ſuffered for us, died, and was buried, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:174907:55"/>to the ſayings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets aroſe again the third day, and aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth at the right hand of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there to judge the quick and the dead, to render immortal happineſs to thoſe that have faith in him, and to the unfaithful ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting puniſhment.</p>
            <p>I then preſented him a Crucifix, and ſaid, Behold this now, and ſee if <hi>Mahomet</hi> did unworthily call the Son of the eternal God by Name of Mercies, when with Arms thus ſtretched forth, he calls poor ſinners to his embraces, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and art burthened with ſins, and I will refreſh you.</hi> And to render him more capable of the Trinity, I pointed to the Sun, ſaying, You have a fair ſimilitude here: as there is but one Sun, that hath form, heat and light; ſo there is but one God the Father, who hath Son,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:174907:56"/>and the Holy Spirit, which you call <hi>Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ahim,</hi> conſiſting of three Perſons equally of one ſubſtance, and from Eternity coexiſting.</p>
            <p>This compariſon wrought in him a belief in God the Father, his onely begotten Son, and the Holy Ghoſt; a Trinity in Unity. And when he had heard my weak diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of God the Father, God the Son, and God the holy Ghoſt, he much admired, with ſaying, <hi>O God, O God; I, nor any of our Sect, could ever imagine, you had ſuch good thoughts of God; for we conceive you live in darkneſs of underſtanding: but by your relation, it ſeems you have great apprehenſions of him; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve well, if you did not neglect our great Prophet of God,</hi> Mahomet. I ſaid, What ſhall we do with the toyes and dreams of <hi>Mahomet?</hi> for beſides Baptiſm and the myſtery of the Trinity, which were had from Chriſtians, we know the <hi>Alcoran</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:174907:56"/>contains nought that tends to Truth. Then I alledged to him the fancies and ſilly trifles of <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s two Angels called <hi>Arot</hi> and <hi>Marot,</hi> whom <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſayes, That God did ſend from Heaven, to miniſter juſtice unto mortal men, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to forbid drinking of wine, and unlawful mixtures with women, &amp; to ſhew the ways to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to no man. Theſe Angels tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing Divine Commandment, were defiled, deceived, and made drunk by a Woman, and ſhewed to <hi>Mahomet</hi> the way to heaven; whom, when God ſaw there, he asked the Angels ſtanding by, who it was that came in that ſhape thither? And the Angels telling him it was by the error of <hi>Arot</hi> &amp; <hi>Marot;</hi> he turn'd the Woman into a Star, and ſent thoſe Angels chained into a well, to be puniſhed everlaſtingly. Divers like ridiculous ſtories I related, as that of the Beaſt <hi>Baraile,</hi> who could ſpeak as
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:174907:57"/>man, who carryed <hi>Mahomet</hi> to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where himſelf confeſſeth to have ſeen great Angels with many heads, and thoſe ſpeaking many Languages in divers Tongues; which is ſufficiently fooliſh, &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy the name of a Prophet; but ſaid, I knew not whether oppreſſed with Wine, in ſleep he dreamed to have ſeen ſuch miracles, or mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroſities in his imaginations. And therefore when he inſerts ſuch fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in his <hi>Alcoran,</hi> he deſerves nor the Title of a Prophet from any reaſonable man.</p>
            <p>Having heard this, ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſhed, he aroſe, and would argue no further: but led me into the Temple, and ſhewed me certain Images carved in wood; and asked me, <hi>If we did worſhip thoſe ſilmilitudes of men, or adore them?</hi> I anſwered, No; think not we worſhip the ſtones or timber wherein theſe figures are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graved; they are uſed and reſpected
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:174907:57"/>onely as records and remembrances to mens mindes of the paſſions and ſufferings of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, for the redemption of our tranſgreſſions: and we worſhip our true God in minde and Spirit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by that Crucifix; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are you denied the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances of your great Princes, and famous men, nor we of holy Saints; but 'tis to give God thanks for their examples of holineſs, and our prayers to imitate their cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and pieties.</p>
            <p>In theſe diſcourſings, he ſpies ſome dogs walking in the Church, and doing ſomething againſt an Altar, (an evil cuſtom, and to be condemned by all) and asked whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was lawful for Beaſts to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our Churches? and bluſhing with ſhame, not knowing how to defend this negligence of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Paſtors, I told him, It was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawful nor ſeemly; and deſired
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:174907:58"/>him to conceive it a meer negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of Officers.</p>
            <p>When he heard this, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended it very much, and deſired me to inſtruct him in our Saviour's Prayer, which I gave him after, in the <hi>Arabian</hi> Dialect.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:174907:58"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>A Lamentation for loſs of Chriſtians deſtroyed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fflicted with an infinite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible ſorrow (moſt high and mighty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of Chriſtian Commonwealths) to ſee the ſad condition, and moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable being of our Brethren under the Turkiſh ſlavery; whereof ſome ſeduced from the boſome of our
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:174907:59"/>Church to heretical unhappineſs; others with civil and hoſtiſe ſword, ſlain, murthered, and caſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Beaſts; others made cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to perpetual ſervitude, and moſt cruelly afflicted. They all by me in lamentable ſobs and groanings complain, O monſtrous, miſchievous ambition of ill men, and wicked covetouſneſs of ruling! How many equal ſouls conſecrated to God's Divine Worſhip, have you betrayed to Death and to the Devil? How many Principalities and Kingdoms of great Kings, and all ſorts of Nobility, have you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed? How many walls of ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Towns have you demoliſhed? How many ſumptuous Palaces and ſtrong ſtately Caſtles have you levelled with the ground? How many lawful Owners have you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected from eminent Eſtates and quiet Conditions, and baniſhed to perpetual diſconſolations?</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:174907:59"/>
            <p>And although I intend not to write the acts of Princes, but to delineate the calamities and trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Captives, I cannot forbear remembrance of that abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſcord of the Earl of <hi>Scrvia,</hi> a potent and proud Prince, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing (a ſhameful foul example of a vitious ambition) with the Baſſa of <hi>Boſnia,</hi> (his neighbour-E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy) and having many Caſtles and ſtrong holds upon the Turkiſh Confines, even to the River <hi>Savus,</hi> (which divides <hi>Illyria</hi> from <hi>Croatia</hi>) and defended all thoſe Provinces which lye between that River and the River <hi>Dravus,</hi> from Turkiſh violences and incurſions: This Earl or Lord of <hi>Servia,</hi> falling into variance and ſome petty contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies with the Nobility of <hi>Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonia,</hi> made friendſhip with the ſaid Baſſa, and joyning their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies both together, invaded the <hi>Sclavonians,</hi> partly at difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:174907:60"/>themſelves, and partly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent; wholly deſtroys them and their Province with fire and ſword, ruining their Towns and Caſtles, ſome by violence and force, ſome by craft and treachery, (cuſtomary with wicked men and Turks) and ſo totally vanquiſhed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered them. And after a few Months had paſſed, this Baſſa be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Earl's rich Provinces, and neighbouring with his, he took or made occaſions to invade him, whom at length he kill'd; and ſo reduced all his Territories under the Turkiſh Government. Thus this ſeditious Atheiſt, Traytor to his Country and his Brethren, moſt ignominiouſly loſt his life: for ſuch are the Turk's rewards to whomſoever by craft, policy, or villanous fraud, he can lay hold on or enſnare. The like was done with ſome Noble-men of <hi>Hungary,</hi> whom they reduced to miſerable captivity.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:174907:60"/>
            <p>Wherefore (moſt Chriſtian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs) the cruelties of this Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ought with all induſtry and vigilance, be both feared and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; leſt conſidering your fair Provinces, and viewing them with a faſcinating eye, he finde you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing, and thereby infeebled, he aſſault you on all ſides, not onely <hi>Candia, Calabria, Malta,</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> but even <hi>Italy, France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi> and prove an univerſal ſcourge and terror to all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. They are wiſe, who by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers harms prevent their own: you are concerned, when your neighbours houſe is fired. But not to trouble you in this kinde, I recommend to you, moſt prudent Governours, the correction and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of this great error, and return to the deplorable calamities and afflictions our Brethren ſuffer under the yoke of Tribute in the Turk's Dominions, where ſome
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:174907:61"/>with chains about their necks, are dragged through ſharp and ſpiny parts of <hi>Thracia</hi> and leſſer <hi>Aſia,</hi> with naked feet, in thirſt and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and if by labour of long journeys, diſeaſes, or other griefs they die (as often happens to men of Quality and bred in eaſe) are hurl'd ſtrip'd in the next ditch, (though not half dead) to the care of ravenous fowls; others, that is, young people of either ſex, endure perforce the filthy luſts of their buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and their fenars, with hideous cryes and howlings of violated and vitiated people; the age of ſix yeers not defending them: others igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in husbandry or Mechanick Arts, and literated men (who are leaſt ſaleable) are for long time driven from Town to Town, from ſtreet to ſtreet; and being once ſold, compell'd with clubs and ſcourges to learn Trades and dayly employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in baſe buſineſſes and griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:174907:61"/>pains: others of more robuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtrength, are made ſlaves to Gallies, tied by the legs with chains, and moſt miſerably tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured; whoſe ſad calamities the power of humane wit cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs in words. And if theſe poor unfortunate ſouls, could have fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known that miſerable being, they'd rarther have choſen a thouſand deaths. If pains of life and death were e'er commix'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yea, if to live long and many days, and die every hour, were ever extant, it is in <hi>Turky: Aegyptian</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, <hi>Babylonian</hi> baniſhment, <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyriack</hi> captivity, <hi>Roman</hi> deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are toyes and trifles to theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities. People, who live as it were in the firy Furnace of the <hi>Chaldean Hur,</hi> and crying up to heaven with ſighs and groans, <hi>O Lord, how long! ariſe and forſake us not in the end:</hi> and when oppreſſed and grieved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all hope, they turn their eyes
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:174907:62"/>again on their own Countries, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in captivity; yet wiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves rather ſlaves there, then where they are: their prayers are not for liberty, but change of place; and for that cauſe, indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent for death or life, they turn Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitives; and ſome leaving their flocks in deſerts, their Oxen at plow, expoſe themſelves to devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; ſome murthering their Maſters and their Children; ſome burning their houſes in revenge; ſome run away, hiding themſelves in Caves and hollow Trees, with fearful wants and dangers; which I here forbear, having given the Reader ſome taſte thereof before. And now they turn their cries to you all Chriſtian Monarchs and Governours of Commonwealths:</p>
            <p>Imploring and beſeeching the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſhould be Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Country, and all ſorts of men belonging to Chriſt his
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:174907:62"/>holy Church, That they uniting all ſects of men in peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, would labour to ſuppreſs this common enemy, and reſtore their Brethren unto liberty.</p>
            <p>Imploring and beſeeching the Emperor and all Imperial Princes, Dukes, Cities, and Nobilities, to cool their hot Calentures of ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and avarice of neighbours rights, and ſet apart domeſtick quarrels, &amp; call together and unite their ſtrengths againſt ſo cruel an Uſurper, and hoſtile Enemy, and labour to defend their preſent, or elſe recover their loſt Territories: and then be aſſured, the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of the Spaniſh Souldiery, the warlike fierceneſs of the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke Provinces, the quick pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Italian wits, the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtiouſneſs and ſtoutneſs of the Germans, will be eaſily perſwaded by the King of Romans, againſt this univerſal Enemy; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:174907:63"/>you withal, No Crown ſits ſo gloriouſly on an Emperour or Princes head, as that which bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a true Title of the Peoples ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and lawful Liberties.</p>
            <p>Imploring and beſeeching the moſt Chriſtian King of <hi>France,</hi> to employ his helping and heroick Arms, in ſafeguard (according to his Title) of his Chriſtian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns liberties, and his own from Turkiſh Tyranny.</p>
            <p>Imploring and beſeeching the moſt mighty and potent Kings of <hi>England, Poland, Denmark, Swede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with all Republicks, Cities, and Corporations Chriſtian, to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and joyne in one, their ſtrengths and powers in war againſt this cankered common Enemy of their Religion, Crowns and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>Imploring and beſeeching, all ſorts of Powers and Authorities ſpiritual and temporal, to imploy
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:174907:63"/>their diligence, and ſhew the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of their callings, by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and amendment of wicked and diſſolute looſe livers, by whom God's wrath is kindled againſt us; and to reduce them to holy Rules of Chriſtian Exerciſes, in living juſtly, ſoberly and religiouſly, and ſo render God a true account of Stewardſhip, and prevent the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries have befallen others drowſie and ſleeping inadvertencies.</p>
            <p>Imploring and beſeeching both young and old, of all ſects and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, godly Chriſtians religious and ſecular, beloved Fathers, dear Brethren, reſpected Friends, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and Companions, That you all, with humble face and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, pure and ſincere hearts and hands, devout mindes, mournfull voyces, and weeping eyes, condole, grieve, and lament the miſeries, the calamities of Turkiſh captives; and call unto the Lord of Hoſts with
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:174907:64"/>violence in pity to his people, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert his anger, and not to give them up to the perpetual rebuke of this wicked Infidel, moſt cruel Enemy of Chriſtian Religion and Liberty; but to inſpire the mindes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings and Governours, with light of his holy Spirit, to reduce them all to unity and concord, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this ravenous and inſatiable Dragon; and grant others ſuch ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, that theſe wretched captives, their Chriſtian Brethren, may be reſtored to liberty in the worſhip and adoration of their God, our Chriſt, and onely ſerve him, who is for ever bleſſed; that at length the Chriſtian World may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed and eaſ'd from ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual ſlavery.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:174907:64"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>An Exhortation againſt the</hi> TURK.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have often mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled with my ſelf, moſt mighty Monarchs, when I conſidered the adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tages which promiſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans victories againſt the <hi>Turk;</hi> and yet inſo many yeers they attempted none, or failed. We have Jeſus Chriſt our God, who in one onely night deſtroyed the hoſt of <hi>Sennacherib;</hi> who drowned <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> who with
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:174907:65"/>a maiden hand of <hi>Judith,</hi> ſtruck off th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> head of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phernes;</hi> and, to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a God, whoſe will is victory. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ary to which, they have a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> a wicked man of life &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, in death, yet hanging in his Sepulchre without Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo as there is as much difference between them, as is between an ever living Son of an ever living God, and a putrid carkaſs of a ſon of a mortal man; that if we diligently examine the nature of each Power and Authority, it would apear like dead men, ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors in ſtrength to living. Now in abilities of bodies, capacities, and gifts of underſtanding, we exceed them; which are good ſtrengths and fortifications againſt an enemy: and yet we are ſtill defeated. Who is more hardy then the <hi>Hungarian?</hi> more ſtout and robuſtious then the <hi>German?</hi> more quick and nimble then the <hi>Frenchmen?</hi> more grave
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:174907:65"/>and ſolid then the <hi>Spaniard?</hi> more cautelous and prudent then the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian?</hi> more valiant and daring then the <hi>Engliſh?</hi> forbearing other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the endowments of whoſe mindes, are better or at leaſt equal. All theſe abilities ſeem able ſingly to get a victory, or at leaſt well to forward it. Courage often with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much force, generoſity of minde, wiſdom, forecaſt, ambition of honour, and policy, oft ſubdues an Enemy; yet notwithſtanding, wretches as we are, amongſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny victorious attributes, we get no victories. Then if we conſider the eaſie preparation &amp; great furnitures of all ſorts of arms, we ſhall appear far to exceed the Turk. Guns of all ſorts have bin our own inventions, and the divers kindes of compleat harneſſes for horſe and foot. The Turks, Perſians Subjects, naked, or half ſo, march forth to war: they have bows, we guns; that is, fire
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:174907:66"/>and thunder: they have arrows, which hardly pierce an Armour; we Cannons, which Rocks cannot withſtand: and yet now ſome <hi>Muſſel-men</hi> have Guns and Gunners; but few, and unskilful.</p>
            <p>Now I pray, what other kinde of people uſe they moſt in Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions? <hi>Scythians</hi> and <hi>Thracians,</hi> who have no <hi>Italian</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Spirits, onely a kinde of inhumane fierceneſs, ignorance and ſtolidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: to theſe are added <hi>Grecians,</hi> loſt men with eaſe and lazineſs; <hi>Aſians,</hi> corrupt with luxury; <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> no leſs in minde then bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, feebled; <hi>Arabians,</hi> bloodleſs, thin, and parboyl'd with the Sun. Who could imagine ſuch-kinde of Souldiery ſhould ſubdue the great advantages and abilities of thoſe fore named Nations? yet (be it ſpoken with grief) our Chriſtians by theſe are overcome, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered into ſervitude, and our great
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:174907:66"/>Captains are forced to bear arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, who were born and bred by Anceſtors to liberty: and in the mean ſeaſon, the <hi>Turk</hi> laughs at us, and the <hi>Jew</hi> rejoyceth.</p>
            <p>Now if I ſhall conſider the Laws and Inſtitutions of Nations, we ſhall be found abundantly ſuperiour in that reſpect: for, what is more righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and divine then the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue and holy Goſpel, written by God's own Finger and his Spirit? what more regular then the Canon-Law? more juſt and equal then the civil Law? Whereas the <hi>Turks</hi> live by Direction &amp; Dictates of the <hi>Alcoran;</hi> a book of ſtuff as fooliſh, as full of vanity; a book of ſport and mirth, if pity for the ſeduced did not allay it; though now ſpread abroad too much, and handled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians; ſo as it may be truely feared, we ſhall learn other Laws, or ſhortly loſe our own, and turn <hi>Turks</hi> in our mindes and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:174907:67"/>approbations, ſooner then in our bodies to their Dominion. What is then the cauſe, having ſo many prerogatives of hopeful war, we are alwayes beaten? why are our Enſigns adorn'd with Crucifixes, fearful formerly to infidels and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, now trampled on &amp; frighted? I ſhall tell you in few words, and truth, We have a God moſt great, moſt good; but alienated from us ſo far, that according to the Prophets ſaying, <hi>We ſcarce are to be named his people:</hi> for why ſhould Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main with us, whom we have rent and torn in far more pieces, then the Souldiers did his Garment, by our hideous Sects, Schiſmes and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies? Beſides his Name, what of him is dear unto us? The very Plow man theſe times is impudent and factious, the Citizen fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and avaritious, the Magiſtrate ſeeks retributions and rewards, the Nobility is riotous and lazy, the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:174907:67"/>Gentry contentious and proud; the Souldier, beyond his pay and ſpoil, craves nothing from the war; let Scepters fall as they will, he is no leſs grievous to friends and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, then Enemies. Church-men beſides pomp eccleſiaſtical, have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Church; not ſanctity, not piety, &amp; ſome not fitting erudition; ſeeking their own, not Chriſt's ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement; that we may ſay with the Prophet, <hi>All have declin'd the ways of God, and are unprofitable; there's none that doth good, not, even one.</hi> Why ſhould we marvel then that Chriſt is not our Friend? We therefore go to war without a God, and what is more calamitous, with God our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary. We carry Bibles &amp; Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes with us, but the crucified by his favour converſeth with our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; our actions therefore periſh, &amp; are involv'd in loſſes And when one Nation fights againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> another is imploy'd in civil wars,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:174907:68"/>calling to his aid, Pagans, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks or Hereticks, more eagerly to oppoſe Chriſt; others tend their home-affairs, to indulge themſelvs in eaſe &amp; voluptuouſneſs. The ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier ſets not forth for Chriſt, but money; which failing, ſoon deſerts the field, &amp; turns home back again. What have we then from thoſe rich Attributes &amp; Eulogies of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, France, England, Spain,</hi> &amp; <hi>Italy,</hi> when the Souldier neglects both God and Honour, and goes to war, as to market, a brothel-houſe, or ſtews, to exerciſe all rapine, ſpoil, and lewdneſs? We have good laws, but evil manners; good furniture of arms, but wicked diſpoſitions: it is our glory to fight among our ſelves; and if we prove coward to enemies, there follows little ſhame or puniſhment. When do we ſee a Souldier quitting Colours or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding, ſeverely handled? which crimes were anciently capital; and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:174907:68"/>whole Legions have been deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and tyth'd for leſs offences. We therefore march with men few in numbers, and thoſe corrupt in manners, againſt millions of men well diſciplin'd; for <hi>Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks</hi> leave their vices in their houſes, from whence we carry ours. In their Pavilions and Tents, no deliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; arms onely, and neceſſary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions: in Chriſtians, all ſorts of Table-delicates, luxury and riot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and commonly, as many light laſcivious Women, as Men. What wonder then if they conquer who are preſerved by ſobriety, parſimony, diligence, fidelity, and obedience? Let them periſh then, who loſe a field to get a prey; who are oftner found amongſt whores, and drunk, then in good actions: but 'tis the fault and error of Supe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iors, when Subjects are not kept in due obſervance; which if Chriſtians were, we could not be inferiour to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:174907:69"/>
               <hi>Turks.</hi> And yet a greater fault, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, Princes themſelves, while they contend in mutual quarrels, are cauſes why they cannot muſter equal forces againſt the <hi>Turk;</hi> for whilſt they fight and combate for ſome little Town or other, after grievous ſtrife, conflictation and exhauſtion of men and treaſure, they grow weak, impoveriſhed and heartleſs. What brave actions might thoſe ſtreams of Chriſtian blood have done, which civil wars moſt impiouſly have drawn out, emptied, and dried up? But 'tis too late to mourn in complaints: <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Affrica</hi> are loſt; <hi>Greece,</hi> extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; <hi>Hungary,</hi> deſperately ſick; <hi>Illyria</hi> and <hi>Sclavonia,</hi> joyned to the <hi>Turk; Auſtria,</hi> much enfeebled; and this plague much threatens <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and Chriſtianity univerſal; and that ſo far, that no great Prince or Monarch ought to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, or think himſelf ſo free, but
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:174907:69"/>that he may be forced to defend his own, without invaſion of his neighbours Territories, whether it pleaſe or not; unleſs they will become of Princes, Servants; of Free-men, Slaves, detained in perpetual chains, or ſlain and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, that their Subjects may want Captains and good Leaders.</p>
            <p>Now, moſt mighty Monarchs and high Governours, for God's cauſe, baniſh from amongſt you all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord &amp; ambitious tyrannies (which are the Devils inſtruments to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain oppreſſions &amp; impieties, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to prolong Gods wrath upon you) and reſtore to each proprietor his due rights and priviledges; and then, as Rivers having free courſe, haſte all ſmoothly to the ſea, &amp; make one mighty body; ſo your ſtrengths united in the bond of peace, would ſtartle, aſtoniſh and drown this great Tyrant <hi>Turk:</hi> which bleſſing on bended knees, I humbly pray
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:174907:70"/>for, and recommend unto the God of Peace. And being reconcil'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your ſelves, if you would ſay as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joſhua, Chuſe you a man, and go and fight with Amalek;</hi> If you would reduce your ſelves to this peace and concord, (which is onely hopeful) and put your help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hands and powers, toward ſo greatly honourable, ſo bleſſed, ſo neceſſary and profitable a war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Turk; who can imagine, but that ye ſhould at leaſt equal the number of his Souldiery, if not far exceed them? He is now ſwell'd up to the very height of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and hath there remained ſo for divers yeers, as if expecting, as if waiting an attempt. All full Seas have their ebbings, all ripe fruits are quickly ſhaken down; there wants nothing to this general and glorious work of Chriſtian Princes, but God's bleſſing, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, and an Heroick courage,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:174907:70"/>brave and maſculine. For the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour can with eaſineſs, raiſe, arm and muſter 50000 horſe, &amp; 100000 foot; the like may hopefully be expected from <hi>France,</hi> from <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> the yet remaining parts of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Illyria,</hi> with the Provinces under the King of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> will raiſe and maintain 60000. Theſe Chriſtian Forces may make 400000 horſe and foot, beſides, the Maritime great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances of <hi>England, Denmark,</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Provinces, <hi>Venetians, Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals,</hi> and <hi>Swedes,</hi> and all other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Commonwealths, who, if once unanimous, and freed from jealouſies, and petty, wretched, wilful home-contentions, the Turkiſh power could no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ye, then <hi>Darius, Alexander; Xerxes, Themiſtocles;</hi> or <hi>Antiochus, Judas Macchabeus:</hi> and having got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten but one victory, and once paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Danube</hi> towards <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:174907:71"/>God being pleaſed, and our lives amended, theſe enemies of our faith would eaſily be trodden down. All <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Thrace,</hi> (where yet great part retain the law of Chriſt) expect with greedineſs the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sword, and readily would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt upon ſuch occaſion, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully aſſault and fight againſt thoſe Lords and Maſters, that have ſo cruelly afflicted them: which cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance alone, would much haſten, if not perfect a ſpeedy victory.</p>
            <p>I would to God, and wiſh hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, moſt Chriſtian Monarchs, That your civil, fruitleſs, home-conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, would permit and ſuffer you ſeriouſly to conſider, and calmly to examine theſe offered motions; you then would finde all mens wills and arms concur with yours; no age, no ſex, no conditions of men would leave your Enſigns: Each <hi>Turk</hi> would have his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:174907:71"/>at home, his Traytor in his Tent, and fugitive in the field. All Chriſtians amongſt them have contemptuous opinions of their arms, and know them onely fitted for light Skirmiſhes, and Picker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; who, if their noiſe, like ſhoals of clamouring Rocks, affright you not, they fly. And whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe God to root out from amongſt us theſe perpetual E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of his faith, and ſend them to their old lurking holes and caves, and corners in <hi>Bythinia,</hi> by the Chriſtian Sword, (according to ſome of their own Prophecies) or elſe to reduce them to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of our Catholick Church; no man can doubt, but in ſhort time the Emperor will be ſeated in his chair at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and inveſted in his Imperial Roman Territories; The King of <hi>Romans</hi> re-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and recover <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Thrace; France,</hi> leſſer <hi>Aſia; Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:174907:72"/>part of <hi>Aegypt; Spain,</hi> part of <hi>Africa; Italy,</hi> all Shores and Banks of the Mediterranean Seas; and laſt, the Pope, as a great Paſtor of the Chriſtian Church, will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol'd &amp; magnifi'd for ſuch an union.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the apprehenſions of all Chriſtian captives under the Turkiſh Tribute, and even Turks themſelves, who have knowledge and long acquaintance in military affairs. And this my ſelf have learned by thirteen yeers experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, The <hi>Turk</hi> is valiant againſt a flying, and flying againſt a valiant Enemy; when therefore he by nature is fugitive, impiety flyes without purſuit. Let God ariſe and ſcatter all his Enemies: let thoſe that hate his Doctrine, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void his preſence: let them like ſmoak vaniſh, and melt like wax againſt the fire: ſo may all Infidels periſh, before the face of God and his holy Church, that
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:174907:72"/>there may be but one Flock, and one Paſtor, Jeſus Chriſt the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. Which grant, Oh ever bleſſed Trinity and Unity, God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:73"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:73"/>
            <head>Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF Oratories. <hi>pag.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>Lent. <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>Circumciſion. <hi>pag.</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>Prieſts. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</item>
               <item>Monks. <hi>pag.</hi> 13.</item>
               <item>Reverence to <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Traditions. <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</item>
               <item>Schools. <hi>pag.</hi> 16.</item>
               <item>Contracts of Marriage. <hi>pag.</hi> 17.</item>
               <item>Of Strangers. <hi>pag.</hi> 19.</item>
               <item>Miracles at <hi>Mecha. pag.</hi> 20.</item>
               <item>Of Alms. <hi>pag.</hi> 23.</item>
               <item>Sacrifices. <hi>pag.</hi> 24.</item>
               <item>Wills and Legacies. <hi>pag.</hi> 25.</item>
               <item>Ceremonies of the dead. <hi>pag.</hi> 26.</item>
               <item>Of a Sepulchre called <hi>Tulbe. pag.</hi> 27.</item>
               <item>Concerning War. <hi>pag.</hi> 29.</item>
               <item>Condition of Noble-men. <hi>pag.</hi> 31.</item>
               <item>Baſſa's and Councellors. <hi>pag.</hi> 33.</item>
               <item>The obedience of Turks to their King. <hi>pag.</hi> 34.</item>
               <item>How ſtrength diminiſhed. <hi>pag.</hi> 36.</item>
               <item>Of Chazalars. <hi>pag.</hi> 37.</item>
               <item>Order of foot. <hi>pag.</hi> 38.</item>
               <item>Pavilions of Turks. <hi>pag.</hi> 40.</item>
               <item>Carriage of Beaſts. <hi>pag.</hi> 42.</item>
               <item>Juſtice in war. <hi>pag.</hi> 44.</item>
               <item>Celebration of Turkiſh Victories. <hi>pag.</hi> 45.</item>
               <item>Of hunting. <hi>pag.</hi> 46.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:174907:74"/>
               <item>Artificers and Husbandmen. <hi>pag.</hi> 48.</item>
               <item>Juſtice amongſt Citizens. <hi>pag.</hi> 49.</item>
               <item>Husbandry. <hi>pag.</hi> 51.</item>
               <item>Diverſitie of Cattle. <hi>pag.</hi> 53.</item>
               <item>Of Houſes. <hi>pag.</hi> 54.</item>
               <item>Garments. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Viands. <hi>pag.</hi> 56.</item>
               <item>Drinks. <hi>pag.</hi> 57.</item>
               <item>Manner of eating. <hi>pag.</hi> 58.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <item>Afflictions of Captives. <hi>pag.</hi> 60.</item>
               <item>Imployment of ſlaves. <hi>pag.</hi> 61.</item>
               <item>Women and Virgins. <hi>pag.</hi> 64.</item>
               <item>Private Priſoners. <hi>pag.</hi> 65.</item>
               <item>Artleſs Priſoners. <hi>pag.</hi> 66.</item>
               <item>Priſoners newly taken. <hi>pag.</hi> 68.</item>
               <item>Expoſed to ſale. <hi>pag.</hi> 69.</item>
               <item>Shepherds. <hi>pag.</hi> 71.</item>
               <item>Fugitives out of <hi>Europe. pag.</hi> 73.</item>
               <item>From <hi>Aſia. Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their puniſhment. <hi>pag.</hi> 75.</item>
               <item>Armenians charity. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Incantations of Turks. <hi>pag,</hi> 76.</item>
               <item>Memory of Chriſt loſt. <hi>pag.</hi> 77.</item>
               <item>Condition of the conquered. <hi>pag.</hi> 78.</item>
               <item>Prieſt and Friers. <hi>pag.</hi> 81.</item>
               <item>Tribute. <hi>pag.</hi> 82.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <item>Narration of a diſpute. <hi>pag.</hi> 85.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <item>Lamentation. <hi>pag.</hi> 97.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <item>An Exhortation. <hi>pag.</hi> 109.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174907:74"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
